<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Jacobs seed or The generation of seekers. And Davids delight : or The excellent on earth. / By the late reverend preacher of the Gospel Jeremiah Burrough.</title>
            <author>Burroughs, Jeremiah, 1599-1646.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 205 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 96 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77990</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B6090</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1162_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210094</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868923</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868923</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121280</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77990)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121280)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 251:E1162[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Jacobs seed or The generation of seekers. And Davids delight : or The excellent on earth. / By the late reverend preacher of the Gospel Jeremiah Burrough.</title>
                  <author>Burroughs, Jeremiah, 1599-1646.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 156 [i.e., 176] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Roger Daniel Printer to the Universitie of Cambridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Cambridge] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Order to print A12v., dated Febr. 27. 1646.</note>
                  <note>Page 176 misnumbered as 156.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "August ye 22th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah LXV, 19 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XVI, 3 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121280:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>JACOBS SEED: Or The Generation of <hi>Seekers.</hi> And DAVIDS DELIGHT: Or The excellent on earth.</p>
            <p>By <hi>The late reverend preacher of the Goſpel</hi> JEREMIAH BURROUGH.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 27.8.</hi>
               </bibl> When thou ſaidſt, Seek ye my face: my heart ſaid unto thee, Thy face, Lord, will I ſeek.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 12.26.</hi>
               </bibl> The righteous is more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent then his neighbour.</q>
            <p>Printed by <hi>Roger Daniel</hi> Printer to the Univerſitie of <hi>Cambridge.</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:121280:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:121280:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THou art preſented here with a ſmall Treatiſe of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend authour, deceaſed; who by his worthy works (as <hi>Abel</hi> by his faith) being dead yet ſpeaketh, <hi>Heb. 11.4.</hi> The work is but of ſmall bulk, yet hath many excellent truths contained in it, concerning two of as neceſſary duties as fall within the compaſſe of a Chriſtians courſe. The ſeeking of Gods face, a thing ſo needfull in theſe trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome dayes, and yet ſo generally ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glected. As alſo concerning the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency in, and the high eſteem that
<pb facs="tcp:121280:3"/> true ſaints have of their fellow-ſaints, which is ſo rare to find in theſe disjoynted and divided times. The work had come abroad ere this, had not the private ends of ſome been an obſtacle in the way. I am confident that of all the works of this worthy authour that have been publiſhed ſince his death, there is none can ſo juſtly challenge him for the father as this, both for matter, and form, as any one that uſed to heare him may perceive. The former part of this work was delivered by him in two ſeverall Sermons (though now thought convenient to be joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as one) The former before the Right Honourable the Earl of
<pb facs="tcp:121280:3"/> 
               <hi>Warwick,</hi> in his own houſe. The latter at <hi>Cree-church</hi> in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> upon Novemb. <hi>5.</hi> the annuall commemoration of our deliverance from the Gunpowder-plot, it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening alſo to be a day of publick humiliation. The laſt was preached in another church in <hi>London.</hi> Accept the work then with the ſame candour as it is intended there, and that thou mayeſt be furthered in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly walking by it is the deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Chriſtian friend.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:121280:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:121280:4"/>
            <head>¶ The contents of the enſuing Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <head>The firſt part on <hi>ISAIAH 65.19.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>THe ſcope of the words <hi>page 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Why the people of God are called the ſeed of Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob <hi>page 2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The words opened <hi>page 5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Doctrine. When God requires a people to ſeek him, he will make it good to them, that it ſhall not be in vain <hi>page 7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>I.</hi> Evidences that it is not in vain to ſeek God.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> The great things recorded of prayer <hi>page 10</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> What the Saints have gotten by prayer <hi>page 11</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> No faithfull ſeeker of God will leave off <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> Wicked men ſeek him not in vain <hi>page 12</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5.</hi> Godly men have given up themſelves to it <hi>page 14</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>6.</hi> Godly men prize the prayers of others <hi>page 15</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>7.</hi> God is found of them that ſought him not <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>8.</hi> God forbids prayer when he will ſhew no mercy <hi>page 16</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>9.</hi> Elſe a praying heart were not alwayes a mercy <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II</hi> What great things prayer doth.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> It is the right exerciſe of our faculties and graces <hi>page 17</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> It is the performance of our duty is creatures <hi>page 17</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> It is a tendring of homage and worſhip to God <hi>page 18</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> It ſhews we are on Gods ſide <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5.</hi> God accepts every faithfull prayer <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>6.</hi> God grants every faithfull petition <hi>page 21</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:121280:5"/>
               <item>III. Wherein the efficacy of prayer lieth.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> God takes pleaſure in doing good <hi>page 25</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> God hath made a covenant with his <hi>page 26</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> Prayer is Gods own work <hi>page 32</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> Right prayer ſeeks God for God <hi>page 33</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5.</hi> It is part of Chriſts purchaſe <hi>page 34</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>6.</hi> Chriſt tenders them up to his Father <hi>page 35</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>7.</hi> God is a God hearing prayer <hi>page 36</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>8.</hi> It is a pouring out the ſpirit to God <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>9.</hi> The ſeed of Jacob are dear to God <hi>page 37</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>10.</hi> It is for Gods honour to heare his people <hi>page 38</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>IV. Objections againſt prayer anſwered.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Object. 1.</hi> We have prayed, and find not the iſſue <hi>page 39</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Anſw. 1.</hi> Remember the times of old <hi>ibid.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> God makes good his promiſe on believing <hi>page 43</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3.</hi> God is great, and we muſt wait <hi>page 44</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>4.</hi> We muſt ſeek God in prayer <hi>page 46</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>5.</hi> God anſwereth not vain prayers <hi>page 47</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>What makes prayers vain <hi>page 50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Object. 2.</hi> It is in vain to pray <hi>page 54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> God heareth the ſeed of Jacob <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> Jacob was mighty in prayer <hi>page 56</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> He feared God <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> His heart was looſe from the creature <hi>page 57</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> He was of a tender ſpirit <hi>page 58</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5.</hi> He repaired to the covenant in his ſtreights <hi>page 59</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>6.</hi> He was of an humble ſpirit <hi>page 60</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>7.</hi> He looked to his former condition <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>8.</hi> He was content with God alone <hi>page 61</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>9.</hi> Jacobs poſterity were all of the Church <hi>page 63</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>10.</hi> Thoſe of Jacobs ſeed have his inheritance <hi>page 68</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>11.</hi> Thoſe of Jacobs ſeed are faithfull in their place <hi>page 70</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:121280:5"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>12.</hi> They are taught of God <hi>page 71</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>13.</hi> They are carefull of their families <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>14.</hi> They are carefull of the Churches good when they be gone <hi>page 72</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Object. 3.</hi> I am a poore wretched creature <hi>page 73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> God hears the prayer of the deſtitute <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Object. 4.</hi> The things we need are great <hi>page 74</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Not to great for God to give <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Object. 5.</hi> But I pray in the time of affliction <hi>page 75</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yet God will heare prayer <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Object. 6.</hi> But my afflictions are for ſinne <hi>page 76</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yet God will heare prayer <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Object. 7.</hi> But God hath determined what he will do <hi>page 77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yet God muſt be ſought by prayer <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>It is not in vain to pray;
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> Becauſe we have had many mercies already <hi>page 79</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> God denyes in granting, &amp; grants in denying <hi>page 80</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3.</hi> God delights in a praying as a prayſing voice <hi>page 81</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>4.</hi> God ſtayes to bring a great deal together <hi>page 82</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>5.</hi> Our veſſels are not ſometimes capable <hi>page 83</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Application. <hi>1.</hi> There are great things that God will do for the Church in theſe latter dayes <hi>page 84</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> The honour of thoſe that are the ſeed of Jacob <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> It is a great priviledge to have a praying friend <hi>page 86</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> To ſet the crown on prayers head in the mercies we have from God <hi>page 88</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> Reproof to thoſe that begin to ſeek God, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue not <hi>page 92</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What God hath done of late, and the uſe of it <hi>page 93</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:121280:6"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> To be humbled <hi>page 95</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> For our unbelief <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> For our murmuring <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> For being diſcouraged in Gods wayes <hi>page 96</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> To love prayer <hi>page 97</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> To be reſolute in Gods cauſe <hi>page 99</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> To give God reall praiſe <hi>page 100</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> Not to let God call on us in vain. <hi>page 102</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The ſecond part on <hi>PSAL. 16.3.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>The ſcope and dependance of the words <hi>page 105</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Doctrine 1. The ſaints of God are the excellent in earth <hi>page 108</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The doctrine opened <hi>page 109</hi>
               </item>
               <item>They are excellent,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> Becauſe they have holineſſe, the image of God <hi>page 111</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>Grace expreſſed in Scripture by foure things.
<list>
                                 <item>The image of God <hi>page 114</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>The life of God <hi>page 114</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>The glory of God <hi>page 114</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>The divine nature <hi>page 114</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> In regard of ſeparating them for God <hi>page 118</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> In regard of their near relation to God <hi>page 121</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> In regard of their great priviledges <hi>page 122</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>5.</hi> In regard of the actions that come from them <hi>page 126</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>6.</hi> In regard of their uſefulneſſe in the world <hi>page 129</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Uſe. <hi>1.</hi> To ſhew the vaſt difference between the godly and the wicked <hi>page 131</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:121280:6"/>
               <item>There will be a time when God will appear for his ſaints <hi>page 132</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Doctrine 2. A gracious heart takes great delight in the ſaints on earth. <hi>page 142</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Joyntly <hi>page 143</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Becauſe their communion is moſt comfortable <hi>page 144</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>1.</hi> In regard of the beauty of grace <hi>ibid.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>2.</hi> In regard of the fragrancy of grace <hi>page 145</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>3.</hi> In regard of their nearneſſe one to another <hi>page 146</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> When the ſaints are joyntly together God hath the ſolemneſt worſhip <hi>page 149</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> God delights in the ſaints joyntly <hi>page 152</hi>
               </item>
               <item>God preſent with his people
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> Becauſe he makes himſelf known to them <hi>page 158</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> He communicates himſelf among them <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> He communicates more choice mercies to them <hi>page 159.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> He communicates his mercies more fully <hi>page 160</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> More powerfully <hi>page 161</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> More univerſally <hi>ibid.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> There is cauſe to delight in them joyntly in regard of their priviledges <hi>page 162</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> They are thoſe we ſhall live with for ever <hi>page 165</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Uſe. To have a high eſteem of the ſaints <hi>page 164</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What delight there will be in the ſaints in heaven <hi>page 173</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:121280:7"/>
            <head>Febr. 27. 1646.</head>
            <p>I have peruſed theſe excellent Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons on <hi>Iſa. 45.19.</hi> and <hi>Pſal. 16.3.</hi> and judging them to be very pious and profitable, I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them well worthy to be printed and publiſhed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Downame.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121280:7"/>
            <head>JACOBS SEED, OR, The Generation of Seekers</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſaiah lxv. 19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>I ſaid not unto the ſeed of Jacob, Seek ye me, in vain.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S Chriſt formerly having the book of this Prophecy given him when he came into the congregation, read a part of it, then ſhut the book, and began his ſermon unto the people; <hi>This day is this Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture fulfilled in your ears,</hi> Luk. 4.21. So may I ſay of this that we have in this propheſie read unto you. Behold, this day hath the Lord fulfilled this word of his in our ears, before our eyes. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is it that we are all here met this day before the Lord, that we may witneſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this good word o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, that <hi>he hath not ſaid to the ſeed of Jacob, Seek ye me, in vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Chapter the Lord promiſeth to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:121280:8"/> raiſe up a great deliverer for his people, and tells them, that they ſhall find him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herwiſe then thoſe that worſhiped Idols, found their gods towards them. That which he ſaith to his people, he ſpeaks it plainly and openly, <hi>I have not ſpoken in ſecret, in a dark place of the earth.</hi> The heathen gods did ſpeak darkly and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guouſly to their worſhippers, that they knew not what to make of their words; but I have not done ſo to you, ſaith God. They would have you worſhip them, but they cannot help you when you have ſo done; it is not ſo with me, <hi>I ſaid not to the ſeed of Jacob, Seek ye me, in vain.</hi> To the ſeed of Jacob, that is, to the Church of God, to the Saints.</p>
            <p>You will ſay, Why are the people of God called <hi>the ſeed of Jacob,</hi> rather then <hi>the ſeed of Abraham,</hi> or <hi>the ſeed of Iſaac? Abraham</hi> is our father; he is the father of the faithfull; but here it is, <hi>the ſeed of Jacob,</hi> not, <hi>of Abraham,</hi> nor <hi>Iſaac.</hi> The reaſons may be theſe two. Firſt, becauſe that all Jacobs poſterity were the Church of God; all Jacobs
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:121280:8"/> children the Patriarchs, were every one of the Church; All that came from A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham were not ſo, Iſhmael was not ſo; All that came from Iſaac were not ſo, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau was not; But all Jacobs children were: therefore ſpeaking of the people of God, of the Church that ſhould be to the end of the world, they are ſaid here to be <hi>the ſeed of Jacob,</hi> rather then <hi>the ſeed of Abraham,</hi> or <hi>of Iſaac,</hi> Then ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>the ſeed of Jacob,</hi> becauſe the Lord is here ſpeaking of the bleſſing of his ſeed, namely in the hearing of their prayers. Now becauſe Jacob was the moſt eminent in prayer, (though Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham and Iſaac no queſtion were mighty with God in prayer yet,) the Scripture doth not put ſuch an eminency either up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Abraham or Iſaac for prayer as upon Jacob. You have the moſt eminent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion for prayer that ever was ſpoken of any man, never the like, Gen. 32.28. <hi>And he ſaid, thy name ſhall be called no more Jacob, but Iſrael: for as a Prince haſt thou power with God and with men, and haſt prevailed.</hi> O how eminent was
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:121280:9"/> he in prayer. Therefore it is rather ſaid, <hi>the ſeed of Jacob,</hi> then <hi>of Abraham</hi> or <hi>Iſaac.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you will ſay, then they ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have been called the ſeed of Iſrael: for his name of Iſrael was given him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his prevailing with God.</p>
            <p>We muſt not be too inquiſitive. Theſe names are uſed promiſcuouſly. But, this is one reaſon that is given, and it ſeemeth to have probability: In Scripture when God ſpeaks of the Church in a low con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, he puts the name of Jacob on them rather then Iſrael: <hi>Fear not, thou worm Jacob:</hi> and it follows, <hi>ye men of Iſrael,</hi> Iſa. 41.14. He puts them in mind of their low condition by this name ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then Iſrael; <hi>Fear not thou worm Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob:</hi> For before Jacobs name was chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, ye know what a low condition, and what ſtreights he was in. So here, the Lord ſpeaking of his Churches delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance out of diſtreſs, he cals them the <hi>ſeed of Jacob,</hi> that they might ſee how by their prayers they were brought from their ſtreights, as Jacob was brought from his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121280:9"/> ſtreights by prayer. When he was Jacob before he was Iſrael, he was in great ſtreights: ſo ſhall the Church be till they ſeek God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſaid not to the Seed of Jacob, ſeek ye me, in vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is, firſt, (as ſome would car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it) I did require is of them, and my requiring did prevail with them: I did not exhort them to it, or require it, and my words fell to the ground and they did not ſeek me; but what I requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of them was effected in them. When God ſpeaks to a people, and they do not what he requires, his word may ſeem to be in vain, there being no efficacy in his words to prevail. But ſaith God, <hi>I did not ſay unto them ſeek ye me in vain.</hi> that is, I called not on my people to ſeek me and they went their own way; but what I ſpake to them prevailed with them, and in them, and they did that which I requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. This is a bleſſed thing when that which God ſaith is not in vain, but we do that which the Lord requires of us. That is the firſt.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:121280:10"/>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>I ſaid not to them, Seek ye me, in vain:</hi> that is, I did not onely tell them that they ſhould ſeek me, but I ſhewed by what way and means they ought to ſeek me in a right manner, that my ſpeaking to them might not be in vain. For if a Miniſter come in Gods name to put you upon any duty, and exhort you to do ſuch and ſuch a thing, and barely tell you what you ſhould do with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſhowing how you ſhould do it, where you ſhall have ſtrength, and in what manner you ſhould do it, he ſhall ſpeak in vain. There are abundance of Sermons in vain, when onely good things are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to people, and they are taught what they ſhould do, but not the way how, and the manner, and where they ſhould have ſtrength to do it: then the word is in vain. But ſaith God, <hi>I ſaid not unto you in vain,</hi> that is, I did not onely bid you ſeek me, but I taught you the way how, and in what manner you ſhould ſeek me.</p>
            <p>Thirdly and laſtly, I ſuppoſe that the principall ſcope of the holy Ghoſt is that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:121280:10"/> which the words plainly preſent to our view; <hi>I required not the ſeed of Jacob to ſeek me to no purpoſe,</hi> that nothing ſhould come of it; but I required that they ſhould ſeek me, and they have found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of good by ſeeking of me.</p>
            <p>So then this point ariſeth plainly out of the words, <hi>When God requires a people to ſeek him, he will make it good to them that it ſhall not be in vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before I open this point I will give you a Scripture or two, one in the old Teſtament, and another in the new, Deut. 4.7. <hi>For what Nation is there ſo great, who hath God ſo nigh unto them as the Lord our God is in all things that we call upon him for?</hi> Here is an experiment of the fruit of ſeeking God; and it is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to ſhew the honour of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the priviledge of the ſeed of Jacob, and the eminent condition they were in. God is nigh to them in all things they call upon him for: therefore they are not required to ſeek God in vain. So Matth. 21.22. <hi>And all things whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ye ſhall ask in prayer, believing, ye
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:121280:11"/> ſhall receive.</hi> A very ſtrange expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Here might ſeem to be a tautolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie. One would think that it had been large enough to have ſaid, <hi>Whatſoever ye ſhall ask, ye ſhall receive:</hi> but here is, <hi>all things, whatſoever.</hi> We would not ſpeak ſo in ordinary language. <hi>I will give you all things whatſoever.</hi> Yet it may be this may be intended, and I believe it is; <hi>And all things,</hi> here is the generall promiſe, that all things that ye ask ye ſhall receive: and <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever,</hi> may referre to particulars, every particular thing that ye ask ye ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive. You will ſay, Any one that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands reaſon or Logick knoweth that particulars are included in the generall. But there is this illogicall reaſoning of unbelief; that though we agree to the premiſes in generall, yet when we come to particulars, we think they will not be made good to us. I ſuppoſe you find your unbelieving hearts ſo irrationall, that though they believe the generall promiſe, yet when it comes to particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and you cannot but ſay that ſuch a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:121280:11"/> particular is in the generall, yet your hearts will not come up to it. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Saviour ſaith not onely, <hi>all things</hi> in generall, but alſo, <hi>whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> in particular. So, Jam. 5.16. <hi>The effectuall fervent prayer of a righteous man availeth much.</hi> There is but one word in the originall, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi> prayer; but it is tranſlated by two, <hi>effectuall, fervent.</hi> Surely then prayer and ſeeking of God is the ordinance which he hath appointed for the turning about of the great affairs of the world. This is the engine that doth it inwardly: There are indeed a great many outward wheeles uſed, but the ſpring of all is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, prayer turns all about. God never made uſe of any created power ſo much as of this. He never did ſuch great things by any created power as by the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of prayer. The Word is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the converting of ſouls, but a great part of the bleſſing of the Word dependeth on prayer.</p>
            <p>In the opening of this point I will Firſt give you ſome evidences of it;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:121280:12"/> Secondly, ſhew you what great things prayer will do. Thirdly, wherein the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy and power of it lyeth. Fourthly, the objections of troubled unbelieving ſpirits againſt it. And then come to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply all. The evidences hereof are firſt the many famous records in Scripture of the noble and glorious exploits of prayer. If any of you ſhould come to me to ask, as that King did of the prophets ſervant, 2. Kings 8.4. <hi>What great things hath thy master done?</hi> ſo what great things hath prayer done in the world? truly we might ſpend houres and dayes in return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you an anſwer, a great part of holy Scripture being ſpent in this very argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And it is a very good exerciſe for you in the night, when you cannot ſleep, or at other times when you are troubled, to do as that King did, Eſther 6.1. call for the book of the Records of prayer. You that reade the Scriptures, mark what you reade. The word of God will tell you how prayer hath ſtopped the Sunne in the firmament, opened heaven, and ſhut it again, raiſed from death to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121280:12"/> life, opened the priſon doores, and what not?</p>
            <p>Secondly, all Gods people are able to tell you great ſtories of what they have gotten by prayer. <hi>This poor man cryed,</hi> ſaith David of himſelf, Pſalm 34.6. <hi>and the Lord heard him.</hi> Who is it that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell hiſtories of Gods gracious deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him upon his ſeeking of him? To be ſure, our Nation hath many things to ſay this way; and every particular godly ſoul hath many things to ſay: they would not loſe their income of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for all the world.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſurely it is not in vain to ſeek God: for there was never any faithfull ſeeker of him that ever would leave off, but would continue as long as he lived ſeeking him: he would ſeek his face ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more; if it had been in vain, he would have left off. When we ſee a Bee ſtick on a Flower, and will not be driven off, or if ſhe be driven off, ſhe will come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, we conclude certainly it finds honey there. So all the Saints of God that have ever ſought God truly, they would never
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:121280:13"/> be beaten off this way. Let the world do what it will, perſecute them, ſet ſpies to watch them in their meetings of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, let it puniſh and impriſon them, let all the malice and rage of men be againſt them, yet they cannot hinder them either from praying in their cloſets, or from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying the benefit of the communion of Saints in prayer. Daniel had rather loſe his life then be kept from his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, though but for a day: but pray he would, and that openly, yea three times a day, as he was wont; he would not forbear one time. He did ſtick to pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er finding honey and ſweetneſſe in it. Oh how unlike are we to Daniel, though the performance of this duty was exceeding hazzardable to Daniel, yet he would not be deterred from it; but every light tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle taketh off our hearts.</p>
            <p>Again, it is not in vain for the <hi>ſeed of Jacob</hi> to ſeek the Lord, for it is not in vain for wicked men to ſeek him, though they are not able to ſeek God as they ough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>The prayer of the wicked is abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable,</hi> Prov. 15.8. That is not to be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121280:13"/> underſtood of the prayer of every man that is unregenerate, <hi>wickedneſſe</hi> is not ſo to be taken in that place. For we know that God hath regarded the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of men unregenerate. The prayers and faſting of Niniveh were regarded of God: the prayer and faſting of Ahab was regarded of God. God hath gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the wicked ſome mercies, he hath looked on them as his creatures. Though God ſeeth enough in their prayers to caſt them off, yet God hath manifeſted his regard to them. Therefore if it be not in vain for the wicked to ſeek the Lord, much leſſe is it in vain for the ſeed of Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob to ſeek him.</p>
            <p>Yea, the Lord heareth the cry of the very Ravens and the beaſts, Pſalme 147.9. and Pſalme 104.21, 27, 28. Therefore the people of Niniveh would have the beaſts eat nothing, that they might cry unto God, Jonah 3.7, 8. Surely if the brute beaſts and the fouls be heard when they cry, it is not in vain for the Seed of Jacob to ſeek God.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:121280:14"/>
            <p>Again, it is evident that it is not in vain, becauſe the people of God that have been wiſe and have converſed with God, and have known much of the mind of God, have given up themſelves and all their ſtrength to this duty. Now it were a weak part and an idle thing for any one to give up his ſtrength and all his might to that which were vanity, and whereby there is no great thing to be obtained. It is ſaid of Jehoſhaphat 2. Chron. 20.3. that <hi>he feared, and ſet himſelf to ſeek the Lord.</hi> It is tranſlated <hi>compoſuit faciem ſuam,</hi> he ſet his face, he gave himſelf up fully to ſeek the Lord. They know what they do that give up themſelves wholly to ſeek God.</p>
            <p>Indeed carnall hearts condemn the people of God becauſe they ſee them ſo earneſt in thoſe things that they think to be vain: For it argueth weakneſſe in any man to give up himſelf with all his ſtrength to things that are vanity, and have no ſtrength in them. Therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe carnall men look upon the way of Religion, as a thing that hath no end, they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:121280:14"/> think it fooliſh for men to be ſo earneſt to give up their ſtrength and their whole ſouls for it: But the Saints of God know what they do when they give themſelves up to ſeek the Lord, they know it is not in vain.</p>
            <p>Again, this is an evidence that there is much advantage by prayer, becauſe men that were wiſe and holy have ſo prized the prayers of the Saints, and made ſuch high account of them. Mark the expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Apoſtle, writing to the Saints for their prayers. Rom. 15.30. <hi>Now I beſeech you, brethren, for the Lord Jeſus Chriſts ſake, and for the love of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that you ſtrive together in prayer with me in your hearts to God for me.</hi> The Apoſtle Paul, ſo great a man, and one that had a mighty ſpirit in prayer, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to private Chriſtians in the Church of Rome, he beſeecheth them for the Lords ſake, and for the love of the Spirit, that they ſtrive in prayer for him: He knew that there was much to be had this way.</p>
            <p>Yea further, God is <hi>found of them
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121280:15"/> that ſought him not,</hi> Iſaiah 65.1. then ſurely it is not in vain for the ſeed of Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob to ſeek him.</p>
            <p>yea yet further, God when he intends to ſhew no mercy, giveth a ſtreight charge to his people not to pray, or he ſhutteth up their hearts that they are not able to pray. This is an argument that prayer is prevalent, becauſe when God will not ſhew mercy, he would not have ſuch a precious thing loſt and ſpent in vain.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, it is not in vain, becauſe if it ſhould, then a praying heart were not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way a mercy from God: but certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is. Therefore though perhaps you cannot find the thing granted that you pray for, yet to have a continuall praying heart, know that it is a great mercy from God. And thoſe that are ſpirituall prize more the continuance of a praying heart many times, then the granting of the thing they pray for. All theſe put together are full eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that it is not in vain to ſeek the Lord.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:121280:15"/>
            <p>There be many other evidences which I paſſe by on purpoſe, that I may have as much time as may be for appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p>But now, wherein doth it appear that it is not in vain to ſeek the Lord? what doth prayer do?</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is not in vain to ſeek God, if there were nothing elſe in prayer but the right exerciſe of the faculties of our ſouls and of our graces; this alone were worth our time. The graces of our ſouls muſt be exerciſed about ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what: Now prayer ſerveth for the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of all graces.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is not in vain if it were nothing but the performance of our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as creatures to God. There are many people that are weary of prayer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have not that by it that they expect: But know that there are two arguments to prayer; the performance of duty, and the obtaining of mercy: If there were but onely the former, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone ſhould ſuffice to keep thee praying as long as thou liveſt.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:121280:16"/>
            <p>Thirdly, it were not in vain if it were nothing but the tendering that homage and worſhip that we ow to God. Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is not onely a duty, but a great part of the worſhip that God hath in the world. While we are worſhiping of God it is worth the time.</p>
            <p>Again, it is not in vain, if there were nothing but this, that we come and ſhew what ſide we are of, that we joyn and ſide with God againſt his adverſaries and for his people. But theſe are not the things here intended.</p>
            <p>Further, it is not in vain, becauſe there is no faithfull prayer that ever was made but God accepts of it in heaven. There was never one of the ſeed of Jacob, that ever put up a faithfull petition to God, but God took it in his hand and read it. A King or any ſuperiour, when you come with a petition may refuſe to take it, but God never refuſeth to take any petition from a faithfull ſoul. Therefore ſaith the Pſalmiſt, Pſal. 6.9. <hi>The Lord hath heard my ſupplication, the Lord will receive my prayer.</hi> He will take it, and look on
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:121280:16"/> it, and read it; &amp; not onely ſo, but he will alſo accept it, and take pleaſure in it: A Prince may take a petition, and look on it, and after frown and ſhew anger in his countenance; but God doth not ſo with the prayers of his people: <hi>The prayer of the upright is his delight,</hi> Prov. 15.8. he never reads a petition that his people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enders, but with a ſmiling countenance. If it be a faithfull petition, he accepts it of them and receives it graciouſly. It is an expreſſion of Luther ſpeaking of the prayer of a contrite heart, <hi>The leaſt ſigh of a contrite heart ſo fills heaven with noiſe, that there is no noyſe of any thing in heaven or earth heard at that time, but onely the noyſe of prayer.</hi> Certainly a faithfull prayer taketh the heart of God very much, yea every faithfull prayer is recorded in heaven. You keep your let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters upon the file, that you may readily find them, when you have occaſion to look on ſuch a letter ſent from ſuch a countrey; ſo God hath his file in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven where all faithfull prayers are kept upon record. As Princes have their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:121280:17"/> offices, where tranſactions between one State &amp; another are kept, ſo the Lord hath his prayer-office, where he keeps all the prayers of his Saints that ever were put up to him. Revel. 8.3. <hi>Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Angel came and ſtood at the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, having a golden cenſer, and there was given him much incenſe, that he ſhould offer it with the prayers of all Saints.</hi> Where were thoſe prayers of all the Saints that he muſt take a cenſer and offer incenſe with? God had them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded with him, and now they were to be offered to him. And ſee what great things follow upon the offering of the prayers of the Saints, verſ. 4. <hi>The ſmoak of the incenſe which came with the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Saints, aſcended up before God out of the Angels hand. And the Angel took the cenſer,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and there were voyces, and thunderings, and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and an earthquake.</hi> Theſe followed upon the prayers of the Saints. It ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the time wherein all ſhould come in remembrance before the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as if an Angel were offering, yea, Chriſt the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:121280:17"/> of the Covenant, hath a time to take the prayers preſented long ago, and to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to God with his own incenſe. They are all recorded in heaven, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are not in vain. When a petition is taken and put upon record, the petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner petitioneth not in vain, his petitionis not thrown out. If a petition be preſented to the Parliament, and they take it, and tell you it ſhall be kept on record, and charge the Clerk to keep it there, and ſay they will take due time to conſider of it, you will not ſay ſuch a petition is in vain. God doth ſo to all his people; he takes their petitions and recordeth them; they are all filed in heaven.</p>
            <p>Yet further, there is no faithfull peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion but God puts his <hi>fiat</hi> to the bottome of it, at the inſtant that it is put up to him. There is a decree in heaven iſſued out for mercy, at the very inſtant that the petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is put up, God dealeth not with us in this kind, as men do who are counted ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry gratious, if they pleaſe to tell us they will conſider of our petition: no; but your petition is preſently gtanted. A petitioner
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:121280:18"/> when there is time taken to conſider of his petition, trembles and ſhakes for fear it ſhould not be granted: but the petitions of the ſeed of Jacob are granted preſently. When <hi>Daniel</hi> had been ſeeking God at the evening ſacrifice, an Angel comes to him, &amp; tells him, that at the beginning of his prayer there was a decree to grant it, and that he was ſent to him at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his prayer, Dan. 9.23. &amp; Pſa. 56.9. <hi>When I cry unto thee, then ſhall mine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies turn back: this I know, for God is for me.</hi> Did not David cry oft, and yet his enemies did not turn their backs when he cryed? He cryed oft when his enemies prevailed: yet he ſaith, <hi>When I cried, then mine enemies turned back:</hi> and <hi>This I know,</hi> why? <hi>for God is for me.</hi> The meaning muſt be this, that at that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant that he cryed, there was a decree in heaven; the thing was done. He look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on it as done, even as certainly as if he had ſeen it with his eyes.</p>
            <p>This is the reaſon that the Saints after they have prayed, though the thing be not actually done, fall to praiſing and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:121280:18"/> of God. We have a notable exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in Jehoſhaphat, of whom we reade 2. Chron. 20.3. that being in a great fear had <hi>ſet himſelf to ſeek the Lord, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed a faſt throughout all Judah.</hi> He did not ſeek God ſlightly, but <hi>ſet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to ſeek the Lord.</hi> And what his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er was, ye may ſee from verſ. 6. to 12. <hi>And Jehoſhaphat ſaid, O Lord God of our fathers, art not thou God in heaven, and ruleſt over all Kingdomes?</hi> Mark how he pleadeth with God for the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant he had made, verſ. 8. Speaking of the Sanctuary they had built for his names ſake; <hi>If when evil commeth upon us, as the ſword, judgement, or peſtilence, or famine, we ſtand before this houſe, and in thy preſence, (for thy name is in this houſe) and cry unto thee in our affliction, then thou wilt hear and help.</hi> He urgeth the promiſe made to Solomon at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of the Temple. For that prayer of Faith which Solomon made, and God accepted, hath the ſtrength of a promiſe in it. <hi>O our God,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>wilt thou not judge them? for we have no might againſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:121280:19"/> this great company that commeth againſt us, neither know we what to do, but our eyes are upon thee.</hi> Though he profeſt that his enemies were ſo many, that he knew not what to do, and that they had no might to reſiſt them, yet after his prayer was done, and before the battell began, <hi>when he had conſulted with the people, he appointed ſingers unto the Lord, and that ſhould praiſe for the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of holineſſe, as they went out before the Army, and to ſay, Praiſe the Lord, for his mercie indureth for ever,</hi> verſ. 21. Mark: he had not yet gotten the victory, the battell was not fought, yet as ſoon as he had ended his prayer, he <hi>praiſed the Lord, for his mercie indureth for ever.</hi> He made account that the thing was done: It was decreed in heaven. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſurely the people of God do not ſeek him in vain.</p>
            <p>Nay, it is not onely decreed, but ere long God will <hi>ſatisfie his people, and fill their longing ſouls with goodneſſe,</hi> Pſal. 107.9. A time ſhall come when they ſhall ſay their prayers are heard, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:121280:19"/> that they have enough. Yea the Lord gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth more ſometimes then his people mention in their prayer, they ask tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall bleſſings, and he beſtoweth ſpirituall; yea he giveth them himſelf, and that is all in all. Surely then the prayers of the Saints are not in vain.</p>
            <p>But wherein lyeth the efficacy of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er? What makes prayer ſo powerfull and preſent with God?</p>
            <p>One thing is, becauſe God delighteth in mercy, and in communicating himſelf to the children of men. He taketh more pleaſure in doing good, then any can in ſeeking it; yea, then any can in enjoying it from him. Our hearts cannot be ſo ſtrongly ſet to ſeek for any mercy from God, as he is to communicate mercy to us. <hi>Who is a God like unto thee, that pardoneth iniquity, and paſſeth by the tranſgreſſion of the remnant of his heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage? he retaineth not his anger for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, becauſe he delighteth in mercy, Mic.</hi> 7.18.</p>
            <p>Another thing that rendreth prayer ſo effectuall, is Gods Covenant and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:121280:20"/> to his people. It was the ſpeech of Archimedes, <hi>Give me a place te ſet my Engine in, and I will ſhake the whole earth.</hi> Let prayer have a ſure foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſet foot on, and it will do mighty things. Now the promiſes are the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of prayer, whereof we have great abundance, Numb. 23. you ſhall find a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of promiſes to the ſeed of Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, under the name of Jacob, when Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam was brought to curſe the people. But in Deut. 33.26. &amp;c. there are admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable promiſes to Jacob. <hi>There is none like unto the God of Jeſhurun, who ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth upon the heaven in thy help, and on the skie in his excellency. The eternall God is his refuge, and underneath are the everlaſting armes: and he ſhall thruſt out the enemy from before thee, and ſhall ſay, Deſtroy them. Iſrael then ſhall dwell in ſafety alone, the fountain of Jacob ſhall be upon a land of Corn and Wine, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo his heavens ſhal drop down dew. Happy art thou O Iſrael, who is like unto thee, O people ſaved by the Lord, the ſhield of thy help, and who is that ſword of thy
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:121280:20"/> excellency, and thine enemies ſhall be found lyars unto thee, and thou ſhalt tread upon their high places.</hi> Here is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to the ſeed of Jacob the fountain of Iſrael, ſo he is called, he ſhall have all things that are good, and God will ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt himſelf, eſpecially againſt his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, Let any of the ſeed of Jacob go and plead this with God, and it cannot be in vain, there muſt be a mighty effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in ſuch a plea, when there are ſuch large promiſes. So in Iſaiah 14.1. there are diverſe promiſes to the ſeed of Jacob. <hi>For the Lord will have mercy on Jacob, and will yet chooſe Iſrael and ſet them in their own land, and the ſtranger ſhall be joyned with them, and they ſhall cleave to the houſe of Jacob, And the people ſhall take them and bring them to their place: and the houſe of Iſrael ſhall poſſeſſe them in the Land of the Lord for ſervants and handmaids: and they ſhall take them ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptives, whoſe captives they were, and they ſhall rule over their oppreſſours. And it ſhall come to paſſe that in the day that the Lord ſhall give thee rest from
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:121280:21"/> thy ſorrow and from thy fear, and from the hard bondage wherein thou waſt made to ſerve,</hi> &amp;c. I make no queſtion but ſome of the ſeed of Jacob, have been pleading this promiſe in prayer where the Lord hath promiſed to have mercy on Iſrael, and to give him reſcue from his ſorrows, and fears, and hard bondage. It was hard bondage that we were made to ſerve in not long ago; here is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe that God will give us reſt from it; &amp; upon the pleading of this promiſe God hath made it good to the ſeed of Jacob.</p>
            <p>And in Iſa, 41.8. there are large pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes in that Chapter to the ſeed of Jacob. <hi>But thou Iſrael my ſervant, Jacob whom I have choſen, the ſeed of Abraham my friend, Thou whom I have taken from the ends of the earth.</hi> It is no matter though they be a poor deſpicable people of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: it is but a few of the poor people do thus, the Gentry and Nobility go an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other way. Verſ. 10. <hi>I have called thee from the chief men of the earth, I left them, and called thee, and ſaid unto thee, thou art my ſervant. I have cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:121280:21"/> thee and not caſt thee away.</hi> Verſ. 10. <hi>Fear thou not, for I am with thee: be not diſmaied, for I am thy God: I will strengthen thee, yea I will help thee, yea I will uphold thee with the right hand of my righteouſneſſe.</hi> Here are five things five times, I, I will ſtrengthen thee, I will uphold thee, I, I, I, I, I, look up to thoſe five l's together, and there are ſeverall expreſſions of help, and ſtrength, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding. How with my hand; with my right hand; that is, with my right hand I am ingaged; I have given thee my hand to help thee; and that ſhall be the hand of my righteouſneſſe. Some men give their hand to their friends when they make promiſes; but the hand that they give it doth not alway prove a hand of righteouſneſſe, but many times a hand of deceit: but when God gives his hand to his people it is a hand of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>I will uphold thee with the hand of my righteouſneſſe.</hi> And what follows Verſ. 11. <hi>Behold, all they that were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed againſt thee ſhall be aſhamed, and confounded.</hi> O God make this good this
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:121280:22"/> day; our enemies are incenſed, they are mad, and rage, and ſwear, and blaſpheme, and ſtamp, and fret, and would have their will, and they would do ſuch things, All that are incenſed againſt thee ſhall be confounded. Some of the ſeed of Jacob have been with God, and have pleaded this promiſe, and that is the efficacy of their prayer, that the enemy is confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. They ſhall be as nothing, and they that ſtrive with thee ſhall periſh. Thou thinkeſt they are a great army, and have great ſtrength: they ſhall be as nothing. v. 12 <hi>Thou ſhalt ſeek them, &amp; ſhalt not find them.</hi> Where is the army now? it is ſo ſcattered that you cannot tell, if you ſeek it you cannot find it, even them that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with thee, they that war againſt thee ſhall be as nothing, and as a thing of nothing. Enquire where the Army is now, you ſhall not find them. <hi>For I the Lord thy God will hold thy right hand ſaying unto thee, Fear not I will help thee,</hi> v. 13. O, but we are weak and poor: <hi>Fear not thou worm Jacob, and ye men of Iſrael, I will help thee, ſaith the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:121280:22"/> Lord,</hi> v. 14. <hi>&amp; thy redeemer the holy one of Iſrael.</hi> v. 15. <hi>Behold I will make thee a new ſharp threſhing inſtrument having teeth, thou ſhalt threſh the mountains and beat them ſmall, and ſhalt make the hills as chaff,</hi> v. 16. <hi>Thou ſhalt fan them, and the wind ſhall carry them away, and the wherlwind ſhall ſcatter them,</hi> and this we ſhould labour to make good. <hi>Thou ſhalt rejoyce in the Lord, and glory in the holy one of Iſrael,</hi> when I have done all this, here is the fruit, not to rejoyce in our Armies, or in outward ſtrength, but to rejoyce in the Lord and to glory in the holy one of Iſrael. Here are promiſes for prayer to ſet foot upon, no marvell it hath ſo much power and efficacy.</p>
            <p>There are divers others, and many things behind of the efficacy of prayer, as it depends upon the promiſe and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant that God hath made with his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: for every promiſe is but a ſeverall branch and expreſſion of the covenant of God: therefore we are to referre them all to the Covenant. I will give you but one Scripture, Jer. 30.10, 11. <hi>Therefore
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:121280:23"/> fear thou not, O my ſervant Jaoob, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be diſmaied O Iſrael: for lo, I will ſave thee from a far, and thy ſeed from the land of their captivity, and Jacob ſhal return and be in reſt and quiet, and none ſhal make him, afraid. For I am with thee ſaith the Lord, to ſave thee: though I make a full end of all nations, whither I have ſcattered thee, yet will I not make a full end of thee: but I will correct thee in meaſure, &amp; will not leave thee altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unpuniſhed.</hi> There is ſomewhat that God doth, but yet ſtill he remembers his promiſe in the middeſt of affliction, that he will leave nothing of that undone: therefore though his people be under great afflictions, the Lord will be good to them according to his promiſe.</p>
            <p>Now again the Lord will regard the prayers of the ſeed of Jacob; the efficacy of their prayers depends upon this, becauſe it is Gods own work. That which is the work of God is not in vain: God made none of his works in vain. Now all their ſeeking of God, It is from God; it is Gods own work, and a moſt glorious
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:121280:23"/> piece of the work of God. Every pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er that comes from the pooreſt of the ſeed of Jacob; every gratious, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full prayer it is a glorious piece Gods work; It is a work of the holy Ghoſt, and therefore it is not in vain.</p>
            <p>Again, as their prayers come from God, they ſeek God from God; ſo they ſeek God for God, they ſeek the Lord for himſelf. If the ſeed of Jacob did ſeek God onely for Corn, and Wine, and Oyle; if they did ſeek him onely for their own eaſe, and outward liberties, and accommodations, and for the lives of their enemies, perhaps they might ſeek in vain. No, but when they ſeek God, they ſeek God for God, and thence they prevail ſo much with God, <hi>Ye ask amiſſe, that ye may ſpend it on your luſts.</hi> James 4.3. You pray to God oft to be delivered from enemies, and you think your prayers (if it be in ſuch a time as this) they come in vain: No marvell if ſo you pray that you may have liberty to trade, and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from taxations; (theſe may be
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:121280:24"/> ſought, but) the houſe of Jacob ſeeks God for his name, that that may not be diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, and for his Goſpel, that that be not taken away, and the power of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe trodden as dirt in the ſtreet, when they ſeek God for God, no marvell if it be not in vain.</p>
            <p>But the great efficacy of prayer is this, it is part of the purchaſe of the bloud of Chriſt: that God might hear the prayers of the Saints, it comes from the merits of Chriſt, it is a part of his purchaſe that God ſhould regard them, it is in his name that we pray, ſo we are taught. It is by Chriſt that we have acceſſe to the throne of grace our priviledge of ſeeking God is that which Chriſt hath purchaſed by his bloud. So that our ſeeking of God is not onely a duty, and beneficiall to us, but it is a high priviledge purchaſed by the bloud of Chriſt; by him we have acceſſe with boldneſs, the word is, with liberty of ſpeech: liberty of ſpeech is by the bloud of Chriſt, that we may come before the Lord, and open our minds fully, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there is a great deal of efficacy in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:121280:24"/> prayer. Whatſoever our prayers are, as they are from us, though they be vain, as they are from us, yet take them as Chriſts purchaſe, here lies the great efficacy of prayer.</p>
            <p>Think not that the efficacy of prayer lies in earneſtneſſe, or enlargement: though it be a comfort, and an evidence that God enlargeth us by his Spirit, (it is not parts that enlarge, but the Spirit) but the virtue of prayer lies not here: the ſtrength whereby prayer doth great things, it lies in the engine lower in ſecret, in the purchaſe of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Again, Chriſt takes all the prayers of the ſeed of Jacob, and renders them up to his Father for acceptance. We have a more glorious way of coming to God then Adam had in innocency, yea in ſome reſpects then the Angels themſelves, by having ſuch an Interceſſor that takes all our prayers and carries them to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Yea, not onely ſo, but he joynes with us to the Father. There is a place in the Hebrews quoted out of the Pſalms, that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:121280:25"/> ſhewes that Chriſt praiſeth God in the congregation; it is not onely the Saints that praiſe God but Chriſt himſelf. Heb. 2.12. <hi>I will declare thy name unto my brethren, in the middeſt of the Church will I ſing praiſes unto thee.</hi> Chriſt in the middeſt of the Church ſings praiſe to God. When people meet to praiſe God, Chriſt praiſeth him. It is a mighty en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement in praiſing God. So in prayer, when we meet to ſeek God Chriſt ſeeks him: for he is at the right hand of the Father, making continuall interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the Saints; Chriſt himſelf joynes with them in the work that they ſeek not in vain.</p>
            <p>Again, it is the ſtile and title that God glories in, to be a God hearing prayer, therefore he will not let it be in vain,</p>
            <p>Again, prayer is the pouring forth of the ſpirit to God, the ſpirit that is ſo beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with the graces of his own ſpirit; now the pouring forth of ſuch a precious ſpirit to God ſo beautified, and principled with the graces of the holy Ghoſt, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly this cannot be in vain. Indeed, the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:121280:25"/> Scripture ſaith, of the heart of the wicked that it is little worth: Let their heart be poured fourth God doth little mind, or regard it: but the heart of the righteous is much worth, it is very precious before God: therefore when their hearts are poured out, and God ſees the beauty and glory of his graces on them, it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding delightfull to him, and ſuch pouring out of their hearts, cannot be in vain. If God have a bottle for all their tears, he hath a bottle alſo for all their expreſſions, and pouring out of their hearts in prayer.</p>
            <p>Further, the exceeding delight that God hath in the ſeed of Jacob, muſt needs cauſe God to regard their ſeeking that it be not in vain. They are his darlings: now there is no man that loves to deny a ſuit to any that he delights in. We have a notable expreſſion concerning the ſeed of Jacob when they pray, <hi>Thou art my King, O God, command deliverance for Jacob.</hi> Pſal. 44. There comes a commanding po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer from God for the deliverance of Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, when Jacob comes to ſue to God.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:121280:26"/>
            <p>Laſtly, it were not for the honour of God to ſend away his people empty, that they ſhould ſeek him in vain. It is repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of Titus, though he were a heathen Emperor, yet he would not that any man ſhould go ſad out of the preſence of the Prince. God accounts it an honour that none ſhould go ſad out of his preſence. Therefore thoſe are called on to rejoyce that ſeek the Lord. <hi>Let the hearts of them rejoyce that ſeek the Lord,</hi> Pſalm. 105.3. not onely let the heart of them rejoyce that find the Lord, that obtain that they ſeek, but thoſe that ſeek the Lord, while they are ſeeking ſhould rejoyce in ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him.</p>
            <p>Well, becauſe I would ſain get to the application of the point, I paſſe by other things, and will onely take away that great objection, and reaſoning, that is in the hearts of men againſt this point.</p>
            <p>You tell us that the prayers of Gods people are not in vain, and by Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy now and then, we have found ſome comfortable hearing from heaven: but ordinarily we find it otherwiſe. How
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:121280:26"/> many prayers have we put up to God, and find not the iſſue? we pray, and pray, and the enemies prevail, though now and then God give us help.</p>
            <p>Now for the taking away of all unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving reaſonings againſt the point, I will not go from the text at this time.</p>
            <p>Therefore the firſt anſwer is this: You ſay you have ſought God, and have not what you would have, and therefore it is in vain: (though perhaps this that you now ſay is vain) yet it makes not the text void. Remember what hath been before: heretofore you have ſought God, and that was not in vain, remember the times of old, let that for the preſent a little ſtay you. It was that that ſtayed the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, he began to reaſon as you do, that he had ſought God in vain, <hi>Will the Lord caſt off for ever? and will he be favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable no more? is his mercy clean gone for ever? doth his promiſe fail for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more?</hi> &amp;c. Pſalm 7, 8. here ſeems to be as much unbelief as is in your reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: but mark what follows. v. 10. <hi>And I ſaid this is my death: but I will remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:121280:27"/> the years of the right hand of the moſt high.</hi> O, it is my ſinne, and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that I ſhould reaſon thus, I conſider not what I do when I reaſon thus: <hi>but I will remember the years of the right hand of the moſt high,</hi> verſ. 11. <hi>I will remember the works of the Lord: ſurely I will remember the wonders of old.</hi> v. 12. <hi>I will meditate alſo of all thy works, and talk of thy doings. Thy way O God is in the ſanctuary: who is ſo great a God as our God? Thou art the God that doeſt wonders, thou haſt declared thy strength among the people,</hi> v. 14. <hi>Thou hast with thine arm redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thy people, the ſons of Jacob &amp; Joſeph.</hi> v. 15. Mark, at length he recovers himſelf with this, though preſent things ſeem to go hard, yet he remembred what God had done, ſo do thou in this caſe. In Iſaiah, you have a complaint of unbelieving hearts, as if God had been ſought in vain. Iſa. 40.27. <hi>Why ſayeſt thou O Jacob, and ſpeakeſt O Iſrael, my way is hid from the Lord, &amp; my judgement is paſſed over from my God</hi> Art thou one of the ſeed of Jacob, &amp; haſt
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:121280:27"/> ſought God, and ſayeſt it is in vain? God reaſons the caſe, and will confute their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief. <hi>Hast thou not known? haſt thou not heard, that the everlaſting God, the Lord, the creator of the ends of the earth, fainteth not, neither is weary? there is no ſearching of his underſtanding. He giveth power to the faint, and to them that have no might he increaſeth strength. Even the youths ſhall faint &amp; be weary, &amp; the young men ſhall utterly fall.</hi> v. 28, 29, 30, 31. But they that wait upon the Lord ſhal renew their ſtrength; they ſhall mount up with wings as Eagles; they ſhall run and not be weary and they ſhall walk and not faint. Hath not God done great things heretofore, in 88. and in the powder plot and at other times? and though we be in ſome ſtreights, remember what God did before.</p>
            <p>This ſhould appeaſe your hearts, what though thou have not preſent audience for the thing thou ſeekeſt: yet think, I deal with a God that hath an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that I cannot ſearch. God it may be lets the adverſary prevail ſometimes, I
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:121280:28"/> cannot tell what glory God may get by it, I cannot conceive how God can bring his own glory about when Iſrael flees be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Philiſtines, But why ſayeſt thou ſo O Jacob? there is no ſearching of Gods underſtanding, God ſees further then thou canſt ſee: that thing that thou thinkeſt will make againſt his name may make for it: therefore lay thine hand upon thine heart. He giveth power to the faint, and to them that have no might. God ſtayes till men have no might, till they faint, and are ready to ſail, and then he comes and helpes them. That is the meaning of that Scripture in Luke, where Chriſt ſaith, God will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge his elect that cry night and day to him, though he tarry, he will avenge them, he will hear their prayers: it is not in vain: But it follows upon it, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding when the Sonne of man comes ſhall he find faith on earrh? I ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily think that that want of faith, hath reference to that very promiſe ſpecially, that God will hear his elect that cry: but God may ſtay ſo long, as that the very
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:121280:28"/> time when God ſhall come to perform it, &amp; ſhall intend to do it, it may be a time when their faith is overcome, and fails in the promiſe, that they begin to give o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and think they have ſought in vain. And uſually the time when God comes to fulfill his promiſe, and to anſwer the prayers of his people, it is that very time when they fail and are ready to ſink. Therefore that may be another argument, it may be thou haſt not believed this promiſe. Thou ſayeſt thou haſt prayed, and thou thinkeſt it is in vain: haſt thou believed this promiſe in the text? haſt thou relyed on it? God hath not ſaid to the ſeed of Jacob, <hi>Seek ye me in vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The word of God ſhall be made good, but how? upon our faith: it ſhall be made good to us upon our believing: though we be never ſo godly, and pray never ſo well, yet if we will have the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes made good, it muſt be upon believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. If thou haſt not laid the weight of thy ſoul on the promiſe, thou haſt no cauſe to ſay that God hath not made his
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:121280:29"/> word good; it may be thou haſt not faith: learn to believe the word, and then thou ſhalt have it fulfilled. Thou wouldeſt have it made good, and then thou wouldeſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it; no, thou muſt firſt believe the word and then expect that God ſhould fulfill his promiſe.</p>
            <p>Again, God is a great God that we ſeek to, and it is fit for us to wait, and to wait long. He is great, &amp; we ſeek great things, and we are poor, mean, vile wretches. God hath his prerogative ſometimes to anſwer preſently, ſometimes not ſo. Elias was a great praying man, he is ſet for an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of prayer; he prayes at one time for fire to come on the ſacrifice, and fire came down preſently; another time he prayed for rain, and then he prayed 7. times, and bowed his head between his knees, and ſent his ſervant, and ſent him again and again. At one time God comes in at the firſt, at another time, not till ſeven times: it is Gods prerogative.</p>
            <p>And take this note; it is a true ſign of a gratious ſpirit, though God defer, yet ſtill for the ſoul to cling to God, to think
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:121280:29"/> well of God, and of the wayes of God, &amp; of the duty of prayer; it is an excellent ſign, &amp; the ready way to find favour with God. You have ſometimes two beggers follow you for alms; one perhaps hath true need, pure need, and is of a ſoft tender ſpirit, the other is a ſturdy rugged beggar, you deny them both; he that hath pure need, &amp; hath a ſoft tender ſpirit, he thinks he is unworthy that the other man ſhould be bountifull to him and he fals a weeping: yet he thinks well of the man, &amp; will be ready to beg of him upon another occaſion, he hath good thoughts of him. But the ſturdy begger rails, &amp; breaks into an angry paſſionate mood, &amp; he will ask no more; who of them is like to prevail, the ſoft ſpirit that hath an ingenious diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, or the ſturdy ſpirit that ſoon breaks off? Thus there are many paſſionate hearts, that are not froward with men, but with God, they come, &amp; ask mercy of God, but their hearts are ſtiff, and froward &amp; ſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, if they have not that they would, they preſently break off, &amp; ſay, why ſhould we wait on God, and cry, it is in vain to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:121280:30"/> ſeek the Lord. But now a gracious, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ingenious diſpoſition, though the thing come not that he prayes for, he ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies God in all, and ſpeaks well of God, and well of prayer, and loves that ſtill, and waits on God in that way: this is the ſoul that is likely to prevail.</p>
            <p>But further, (to anſwer from the text) it may be thou haſt not ſought God, <hi>Seek ye me,</hi> ſaith God. It may be it is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what elſe that thou haſt ſought in prayer then God: though thou name God in thy prayer, it may be thy heart hath been after creature-helps, and thou haſt made more account of the help of the creature, of Armies, and ſtrength, thou haſt made account that they would do it rather then prayer; and if there be no help but prayer, thou thinkeſt it but a dry bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe.</p>
            <p>A carnall hearted man when he hears of an army of twenty thouſand men well clothed and the like, he thinks much may be done, but for the prayers of Gods people they think they be nothing. Now if thou have ſought help by creatures,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:121280:30"/> rather then by God, thou haſt not ſought God all the while, Or if it have been but outward ſafety, that thou haſt ſought and not the face of God, thou haſt not ſought God, <hi>Seek my face,</hi> ſaith God, Pſalm 27. <hi>This is the generation of them that ſeek thy face, O Jacob.</hi> Pſalm 24. Thou ſeekeſt not God, without thou ſeek Gods face, without thou ſeek God for himſelf. And ordinarily, God is not ſought, but thy eſtate is ſought; and thou cryeſt out for the danger thou art in. Therefore thou haſt no cauſe to ſay, it is in vain, look to thy prayers, take up thy prayers again. Do as the fiſhermen do; if they find that there comes nothing up, that they do not catch, they take up their net, it may be there is a hole, a rent in the net. And ſo the Angler, if the fiſh do not bite he takes up the bait, it may be there is ſomewhat wanting on the hook. So look to thy prayers, it may be it is not God that thou haſt ſought, take them up and ſee what is amiſſe in them.</p>
            <p>Another anſwer is this, it may be thy prayers
<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:121280:31"/> fore no marvell if nothing but vain come of them. <hi>Surely, God will not hear vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> Job 35.13. If there be nothing but vanity, how canſt thou expect that God ſhould hear them? The word here, <hi>in vain,</hi> it is the ſame word in Geneſis 1. <hi>At the firſt all was without form and void;</hi> a confuſed chaos. So ordinarily our prayers are without form, and void, that is, there is nothing but vanity, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed lump, a chaos. Not that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards ſo much the ſetting of a mans words in form handſomely: for the grones and ſighs of the ſpirit of God are accepted, though they be not methodicall, as the making of a ſpeech to men; God looks not to that. But they are without form, and void, that is, that is a vain thing that hath no end or not a good end. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pray, and they know not why, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe others do; but they propound not the true end of prayer.</p>
            <p>I appeal to thy conſcience; when thou haſt gone to pray to God, haſt thou pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded this end? I am going to tender up that worſhip and homage, that I a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:121280:31"/> poor creature, ow to the infinite glorious firſt being of all things, you call your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies ſometimes to come to prayer, &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver think what you do, what you aim at. I and my family are now going to ſeek the great God in prayer, I am now going to joyn with my father or my maſter, now that we are altogether in this fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to tender up that worſhip and homage that we poor creatures ow to that infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite glorious firſt being of all things whereby to teſtifie our high reſpect, and eſteem of him. Now if thy prayer be a cuſtomary way of prayer it is vanity, it hath not a right end.</p>
            <p>It may be thou goeſt to prayer meerly to ſatisfie conſcience. Or ſome have this by end in prayer, a wicked end, that is, they think to ſatisfie God for their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſinfull wicked wayes. They take li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie in company to drink and pleaſe the fleſh, and as they ſerved themſelves then, ſo now they will ſerve God, and ſet one againſt another. Sometimes they will give liberty to the fleſh to take content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that way, but they will not alway
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:121280:32"/> do ſo, ſometime they will be devout and ſerve God. There is no man ſo wicked as to be alwayes in the acts of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but they think God muſt have his turn, and they muſt have their turn ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times. And this is the prayer of many people, to put their ſinnes in one ſcale, and ſo many devout prayers in the other ſcale, and the one ſhall poize the other. This is vanity, this is not the end of prayer.</p>
            <p>Then a thing is vain, when it is empty, when there is not ſubſtance in it: Now when the heart is empty in prayer, there are words, and they are wind, the Lord ſees not the ſtrength of thy ſpirit, thou doſt not ſet thy ſelf before the Lord in prayer, thy expreſſions are meerly empty: God doth not ſee thy expreſſions filled with the graces of the Spirit: this is va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: Take heed of vain expreſſions, when there is nothing but nature in prayer; though there be never ſo much earneſtneſſe in prayer, if there be but a naturall ſpirit it is vanity, we muſt pray in the ſpirit as the Scripture ſpeaks.</p>
            <p>And take heed of ſluggiſhneſſe in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:121280:32"/> that makes it vanity. The breath that comes from life in mans body is warm, but the breath that comes from bellows is artificiall and cold, ſome mens breath in prayer is artificiall and cold, but the prayer that comes from life, is warm breath that comes up to God.</p>
            <p>Again, vanity is this, when all is eaten out with vain thoughts, thy heart roves in prayer, thou knoweſt not where thou art, thou canſt not call that which thou makeſt a prayer. A prayer with vain thoughts is like bear, or wine that is dead, and hath loſt the ſpirits. Vain thoughts are worms that eat out the ſtrength of a duty: would you preſent a diſh to your ſuperiour that were worm-eaten, or that were gnawn on before? when we let out our thoughts in duties, and preſent them to God, they are worm-eaten, and torn, the ſtrength of them is quite gone.</p>
            <p>And after you have prayed, take heed that you make not your prayers vain, by not looking after them, for the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of them; or by being proud of your prayers and gifts, by reſting in them.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:121280:33"/>
            <p>And it is vanity when thou undo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt all as ſoon as thou haſt done, by going contrary to thy prayer in thy life, not adding watchfulneſſe to pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. If a man take pains to weave a web, and ſpend ſo many hours in it, and then ravell it out, this man ſpends his time in vain. So do moſt people with their prayers, they pray for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and grace, and as ſoon as they have done they go quite contrary and ravell and undo all; is not this vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? No marvell if thou think it in vain, when there is nothing but vanity in thy prayers.</p>
            <p>And take heed that you make not the prayers of others vain. Luther writes to Melancthon angerly, in regard of his fear of the power of his adverſaries, ſaith he, You make our prayers void. So it may be ſaid of many that are cold, and luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm, and dead-hearted, and do not take to heart the cauſe of God; that fear the diſpleaſure of this body, and that body; you make our prayers void. You that have praying friends, it may be fathers,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:121280:33"/> and mothers that are dead whoſe pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are put up in heaven, take heed that you make not their prayers void; that you give them not cauſe if they ſhould come to live again from the dead to weep and cry out, O how are our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers made void by the prayers of ſuch and ſuch.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, Lord, what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of us? we have abundance of vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in our prayers.</p>
            <p>Therefore, that you may not be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, know, that though there be many vain thoughts in prayer, yet if there be ſighing and mourning, and humbling of the ſoul, and panting of the heart after God in groning, and ſighing, and though there be a mixture of vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yet there is a working of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, and of grace in the heart after God; know that the Lord will not charge this vanity on thee, the Lord will do away thy ſinne, therefore let not that diſcourage thee. The efficacy lies not in the excellency of thy prayer, but in the merits of Chriſt, and his mediation:
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:121280:34"/> Onely Chriſt will have ſomewhat of thy ſelf in thy prayer, he will haue thy heart pant, and work after him: but there may be abundance of vanity, thou draweſt a line, and makeſt a blot, and another line. and another blot, Chriſt draws all fair again, and preſents it to his Father.</p>
            <p>But another queſtion is this, you ſay it is in vain to pray. Can you make good that you are one of the ſeed of Jacob? this priviledge belongs to them, it may be you are of the ſeed of Eſau.</p>
            <p>The ſeed of Eſau, what is that?</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle ſpeaks of Eſau what his guiſe was. Heb. 12.6. and ſaith, <hi>Take heed that none of you be ſuch as Eſau, leſt there be any fornicatour or profane perſon as Eſau, who for one morſell of meat ſold his birth-right.</hi> Now if thou prove a fornicatour thou art of the ſeed of Eſau, or a profane perſon; what is that? for one morſell of meat he ſold his birth-right, that is, to pleaſe, and ſatisfie and conſent the fleſh he ſold his birth-right, that was the land of Canaan, and ſo ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pified the priviledges of the Church of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:121280:34"/> Gods, and even a type of heaven it was. His birthright had a ſpirituall meaning, is had reference to the ſpirituall privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, that the Saints of God have to this day in all the ordinances of God.</p>
            <p>That man or woman that prizeth any carnall contentment before ſpirituall pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, they are of the ſeed of Eſau, and not of Jacob. Thou thinkeſt there is ſome favour in money, and in a good trade, and in good chear, and ſuch a day as this November 5. is better then a faſt-day, becauſe of the good chear: but for the ſpirituall duties of this day, to come and magnifie God, and to attend upon his word, thou thinkeſt they are circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and by-matters, and thou art trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled if the Sermon be too long to hinder thee of thy dinner; thou art a prophane Eſau, all that I have ſaid belongs not to thee, thou doſt not belong to Jacob but to Eſau, that preferreſt carnall things for the fleſh before the ſpirituall priviledges of the Saints.</p>
            <p>But how ſhall I know that I am one of the ſeed of Jacob?</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:121280:35"/>
            <p>How do you know ſuch an ones child, but by his likeneſſe to his father? One that hath the ſpirit of Jacob is of the ſeed of Jacob. There are many things that the Scripture ſpeaks concerning Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, and ſee if you do anſwer them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Jacob was a mighty man in prayer, he was a wreſtler with God, and he wreſtled till the day broke, and was as ſtrong at the laſt as at the firſt: haſt thou the ſpirit of thy father Jacob? art thou not diſcouraged in prayer? though mercy come, not preſently yet doſt thou wreſtle all night, and reſolve whatſoever come if thou die, thou wilt die wreſtling; here is a child like the father, therefore thou art of the ſeed of Jacob.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Jacob was one that feared God, when God appeared to him he looked on the preſence of God as dreadfull, <hi>How dreadfull is this place?</hi> Geneſis 28. becauſe God was there. So doſt thou look on the preſence of God as dreadfull, that thou canſt ſay the fear of the great God is on thy ſoul: when
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:121280:35"/> thou comeſt into his preſence? mark, for this is that expreſſion in the Pſalm, <hi>Ye that fear the Lord praiſe him, all the ſeed of Jacob glorifie him, and fear him all ye ſeed of Iſrael,</hi> Pſalm. 22.23. If you will be ſure not to ſeek God in vain, but that you may praiſe him in ſeeking him, fear the Lord all the ſeed of Jacob.</p>
            <p>Hence we reade that when there was an oath between Laban and him, the oath that he took was, he ſwore by the fear of his father Iſaac. God was the fear of Iſaac, and Iſaac ſo feared God, that he had his denomination from his fear: Now Jacob ſwearing by the fear of his father Iſaac, that notes that the fear of God was upon Jacob, as it was upon his father. And doſt thou walk in the fear of God? Haſt thou not a bold ſpirit that goes in ſlight, preſumptuous, bold baſe wayes? This is not like Jacob, he looked on Gods preſence as terrible.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Jacobs heart was diſingaged from the creature, a little of the creature would ſerve his turn, Ge. 28. <hi>Lord,</hi> ſaith he,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:121280:36"/> if thou wilt give me meat to eat and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to put on. He looked no further, he minded no great matters. Therefore in Pſalm. 24. there the generation of Jacob is ſet out, and one thing is, he that hath not lift up his ſoul to vanity. The men of the world have great things in their eyes, they are vanity in Gods eye, though they be great in theirs, and they lift up their hearts to them. Now the ſonnes of Jacob do not lift up their hearts to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, though the things of the world be preſent, their hearts ſtirre not, they riſe not; but if God and Chriſt, and heavenly things be preſented, their hearts are lifted up. If thy heart be lifted up to vanity, if thy heart be as iron and the vanities of the world come and draw it up, thou art not a ſonne of Jacob: a little would ſerve Jacob though he were a great heir, <hi>He was a plain man and dwelt in tents,</hi> Gen. 25. and had a plain ſpirit, he did not look after great things; whereas Eſau looked after great things abroad.</p>
            <p>Again, he was one of a tender ſpirit: therefore where it is ſaid he prevailed
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:121280:36"/> with the Angel, it is ſaid he wept, and made ſupplication unto him, he found him in Bethel, and there he ſpake with us. That ſtory of Jacob concerns us how God dealt with our Father. If now thou have a tender ſpirit as he had; if when thou goeſt into the preſence of God thou find thy ſpirit yield and melt, and relent, thou art one like thy father Jacob.</p>
            <p>Again further, Jacob did in the time of his ſtreights repair to the covenant, that was a great ſatisfaction to his heart; he looked to the covenant, he faſtned on that, and there he held as the main ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of his ſpirit. Gen. 32.9. And Jacob ſaid, <hi>O God of my father Abraham, and God of my father Iſaac, the Lord which ſaid'st unto me return unto thy countrey, and to thy kindred, and I will deal well with thee</hi> &amp;c. He heard that Eſau was coming againſt him with a great many; and what doth Jacob? he gets him to God, <hi>O God of my father Abraham, and of my father Iſaac, the Lord which ſaid unto me return into thy countrey,</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:121280:37"/> &amp;c. He repairs to the Covenant: <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thy Covenant with Abraham and Iſaac,</hi> and with me too, I went on thy word. Here was the guiſe of Jacob: canſt thou in a ſtraight get thee too a word, and a promiſe, and brood thy ſoul over it, and claſp it cloſe, &amp; ſay this is the promiſe that muſt, and will do me good?</p>
            <p>Again, Jacob was of an humble ſpirit, I am not worthy of the leaſt of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. He admired at the mercy of God that he had any thing, and Gods mercies made him more humble; this is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent diſpoſition, we are many times humble and lowly when we are under the hand of God in affliction: but when mercies make us humble, that the more God is gracious the more vile we are in our own eyes, this is excellent.</p>
            <p>And he looked back to his former condition, he looked upon his poor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and gives God the glory: I paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed over this Jordan with my ſtaffe; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you came with your ſtaff, and God hath given you two bands, you are grown great, are you willing to think of it, and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:121280:37"/> to acknowledge the poor eſtate that once you were in, and to give God the glory, I was thus, and thus, of poore parentage, and ſee how God hath dealt with me.</p>
            <p>Another thing remarkable is, that Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob contented himſelf with God alone, he accounted that he had enough in God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, though all were taken from him, he did not look upon himſelf as undone, but he had that that might make him for ever. In Gen. 33. compare the 9. and 11. verſes, you ſhall find a notable diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between Eſau and Jacob, yet the word in our books is the ſame, but this Scripture is much wronged by the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. In v. 8. Eſau when he comes to Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, when Jacob would have given him his preſent, ſaith he, <hi>what meaneſt thou by all theſe droves which I met?</hi> he ſaid, <hi>theſe are to find grace in the ſight of my lord:</hi> and Eſau ſaid, <hi>I have enough my brother,</hi> It was a ſtrange ſpeech of Eſau: A covetous wretch that is alway pyning and murmuring for having no more, and thinks he ſhall want before he dye, he doth not come ſo farre as Eſau,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:121280:38"/> and Eſau could ſay, <hi>I have enough,</hi> are there not many of you that never ſay you have enough? I pray thee take my preſent ſaith Jacob, for I have all things, nay ſaith Eſau, I have enough. The one ſaith I have enough, the other ſaith I have all things, for ſo the word is <hi>Col;</hi> Eſau had enough, he did not want, he had meat and drink, and he ſaw none to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt him, he was ſatisfied with his eſtate, as his portion; he had enough, he cared for nothing more, they might talk of other things, but that was enough to him. Jacob comes, and ſaith I have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough; but this was another man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of enough: Eſaus enough is his eſtate, but Jacobs enough is God, for he ſaith, <hi>I have all,</hi> Jacob was meaner for his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward condition then Eſau, for he had nothing but what he had gotten in hard ſervitude. Now Eſau ſaith, <hi>I have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough,</hi> Jacob ſaith, <hi>I have all:</hi> that is, God is enough in the want of all, if E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau ſhould ſtrip him of all he had, yet he had all in God. Now one that is of the ſeed of Jacob, in the time of want (as
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:121280:38"/> ſome of you may be plundered, and then all is gone you ſay; no, if thou be of the ſeed of Jacob) if thou have God thou haſt all. There is ſuch a promiſe, <hi>He that overcometh, ſhall inherit all things.</hi> How is that? <hi>and I will be his God.</hi> Revel. 21.7. Therefore whatſoever thou wanteſt if God be thine, if thou be Gods child, thou haſt all.</p>
            <p>Further, one of the ſeed of Jacob is one of the Church of God: for all Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs poſterity was ſo: therefore the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in Ruth is, <hi>The Lord bleſſe thee like Rachel and Leah,</hi> which two did build up the houſe of Iſrael. Why is it not, the Lord bleſſe thee as Rebeccah, or Sarah, but as Rachel and Leah. (It was a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon a marriage condition) the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe from Rachel and Leah, came onely thoſe that were of the Church, that were members of the Church of God; but there came others from Rebec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cah, and of Sarah came onely Iſaac, but Abrahams poſterity was otherwiſe. And that Church that was then was but a type of that which ſhould be after; that is of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:121280:39"/> a company of people elected, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out from the world to be partakers of the Priviledges of Jeſus Chriſt. The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Jews, the ſeed of Jacob were the Church of God, as the ſeed of ſuch an one. And this typified the Church that ſhould be after; a company that are taken out of the world, to partake of the priviledges of Jeſus Chriſt. Canſt thou ſay that thou art of the Church? The word that we tranſlate Church is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany that is called out from the world. Canſt thou ever tell of a work of God ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parating thee from the world, that when thou wenteſt according to the world, God gave thee a mighty call that made a ſeparation between thee and the world? For it is ſaid ſo of the ſeed of Jacob, Numb. 23.9. <hi>From the tops of the rocks I ſaw him, and beheld him, lo, the people ſhall dwell alone, they ſhall not be reckoned among the Nations, they ſhall be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the nations.</hi> All the ſeed of Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob are called out of the world, they are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from them by a mighty work of God to partake of Chriſt, and be a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of him.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:121280:39"/>
            <p>And upon this, ſuch an one mightily longs after all the outward priviledges of the Church, to enjoy all the outward or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Chriſt after his way, thoſe that are of the ſeed of Jacob, they prize the excellency of Jacob as the greateſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, their hearts are towards it, and they rejoyce in that above all the excellency in the world. If you ask what this excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Jacob is? It is the joyning of Gods people in the way of ordinances, and duties of Gods worſhip in the puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of them. This in Scripture is called the excellency of Jacob, Pſal. 47.4. <hi>He ſhall chuſe our inheritance for us, the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Jacob whom he loved.</hi> It is an excellent Scripture. O, it is a bleſſed thing to give all to God, to let God chuſe our inheritance. What is our inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance? The excellency of Jacob whom he loved. What was that? The worſhip of God, and his ordinances, joyning with the people of God in the way of his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, in his temple, thoſe were the things that were the ordinances of God in thoſe times; thoſe are called the excellency of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:121280:40"/> Jacob; and ſo it is now the excellency of a people to enjoy Gods ordinancies.</p>
            <p>You have another expreſſion to the ſame purpoſe. <hi>And I will bring forth a ſeed out of Jacob, and out of Judah an inheritour of my mountain, and mine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect ſhall inherit it, and my ſervants ſhall dwell there.</hi> Iſaiah 65.9. What is the mountain of God? Gods Ordinances in his Church, <hi>I will bring a ſeed out of Jacob, and Judah, and they ſhall inherit my moantain.</hi> So that the greateſt inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the ſeed of Jacob is the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the Lord: communion with the Church of God, and his ordinances: if you be of the ſeed of Jacob, your hearts prize, and rejoyce in this, and that you have in Pſal. 24. verſ. 3, 4, 5. you ſhall find how the ſeed of Jacob prize the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of God in his Ordinances, <hi>Who ſhall aſcend into the hill of the Lord? who ſhall ſtand in his holy place? He that hath clean hands, and a pure heart; who hath not lift up his ſoul unto vanity, nor ſworn deceitfully. He ſhall receive the bleſſing from the Lord, and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:121280:40"/> from the God of his ſalvation. This is the generation of them that ſeek him: that ſeek thy face O Jacob.</hi> It is ſo in the book: but the particle O, is not in the originall: and therefore it may be read thus, <hi>That ſeek the face of Jacob;</hi> it may be read in the Genitive caſe, as well as in the Vocative. <hi>This is the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of them that ſeek him, even of Jacob,</hi> and then he turns to God, <hi>that ſeek thy face:</hi> but becauſe his heart was full of this, of ſeeking Gods face, (though he intend to mention what generation it was, the generation of Jacob) he puts in that before, the generation of Jacob that ſeek thy face: that is, this is the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration that ſo prize God in his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and account it ſuch a bleſſing of God; that joyn themſelves to the Church of God, and ſet up his ordinances and wayes; this is the bleſſed generation, theſe are thoſe that ſeek God truly. We ſeek not God truly unleſſe we ſeek him in his own wayes, unleſſe we ſeek him in all his ordinances, we cannot comfort our ſouls that we ſeek him in truth. For as in
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:121280:41"/> the way of obedience, we cannot have comfort in our obedience that it is true, except it be univerſall to all Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, ſo we cannot have comfort in our ſeeking that it is true, except it be in all his ordinances, and wayes: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt be of the generation of them that ſeek the face of the Church, that ſeek thy face O Jacob. So it follows in that place, <hi>lift up your heads O ye gates, and be ye lift up ye everlasting doors, that the King of glory may come in.</hi> Where ſhould the King of glory come but into his Church? <hi>Who is the King of glory? The Lord, ſtrong and almighty:</hi> ſtill the Church is called on to entertain Chriſt in his glory, ſo this is ſpoken of the Church. Thus you may know, whether you be of the ſeed of Jacob.</p>
            <p>Again, if you be the ſeed of Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob you have the inheritance of Jacob, and account it your inheritance. What was Jacobs inheritance? Deuter. 33.2. <hi>The Lord came from Sinai and from his right hand came a fiery law.</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:121280:41"/> The law of God is a fiery law; yet in verſe 4. <hi>Moſes commanded us a law, even the inheritance of the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Jacob.</hi> So that though the law be a fiery law, a ſtrict law, a ſevere law, yet it is the inheritance of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of Jacob. If you be of the congregation of Jacob you account the law of God to be part of your inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: not onely to be that which you are bound to, that you muſt obey whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you will or no, but you rejoyce in the law of God as your inheritance. For my part I know not a more ſure note of a gracious heart then this; one that rejoyceth in Gods law as his inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance: as you know what expreſſions David hath, he rejoyced in it more then in Gold and Silver, more then in the honey, and the honey-comb. It is one thing to obey Gods Law, and another to rejoyce in it as an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. If thou be of the ſeed of Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, thou haſt the inheritance of the ſeed of Jacob.</p>
            <p>Another is, he that is of the ſeed of Jacob
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:121280:42"/> is faithfull in the place that God hath ſet him. Jacob in ſerving of Laban, Gen. 31.6. though he were churliſh, he profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that withall his power he ſerved his father. It is an excellent text for ſervants; you would fain have time to ſeek God, and God forbid but there ſhould be ſome time allowed the pooreſt and meaneſt ſervant to ſeek God alone. But art thou of the ſeed of Jacob? then be like him in this, to ſerve with all thy power, though thou have a froward maſter or miſtris, as Laban was, though they uſe you hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet ſhew godlineſſe in that relation. And for ſervants to ſeem godly, he muſt go hear, this Sermon, this man, and the other man, and be very earneſt: (I blame them not for loving the word and deſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it: but for ſervants to be earneſt in hearing the word, and injoying the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and crying out againſt ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Antichriſtianiſme, and yet be ſluggiſh, and unfaithfull in their ſervice, and ſo as to give juſt offence to their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, it is a diſhonour. Shew your godlineſſe in your relation: certainly
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:121280:42"/> there is no man or woman godly, but thoſe that are ſo in the relations and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that they are ſet in: therefore mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt your ſelves thus to be the ſeed of Jacob.</p>
            <p>Again, the ſeed of Jacob is a taught ſeed. God teacheth them, Pſal, 147.19. <hi>He hath not dealt ſo with other nations, he gave his law to Jacob, and his word to Iſrael.</hi> So in Deut. 33.10 <hi>Levi is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to teach Jacob.</hi> There is never a one of the ſeed of Jacob that is ignorant, that is a fool in matters of religion, he is taught.</p>
            <p>And then, one of the ſeed of Jacob, is one that hath a care of his family: ſo we reade of Jacob, Gen. 35.1. <hi>God ſaid to Jacob, Ariſe, go up to Bethel, and dwell there, and make there an altar unto God that appeared unto thee when thou fled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt from the face of Eſau thy brother. Then ſaid Jacob to his houſhold and to all that were with him, put away the ſtrange gods that are among you, and be clean,</hi> &amp;c. When he was to go into Gods preſence, he laboured to reform his fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:121280:43"/> When God calls you to faſt dayes, and to the Sacrament, do you cleanſe your families, do you look what evils are in your families, and put out your po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to cleanſe them?</p>
            <p>But there is one more that I may not omit, that is, Jacob, when he was to die, though he himſelf was to go the way of all fleſh, yet this was his great comfort and the comfort of thoſe that he left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, that God would make good his word to his Church and people, Gen. 48.21. <hi>and Iſrael ſaid to Joſeph, Behold, I die, but God will viſit you, and bring you again to the land of your fathers.</hi> Behold I die, but I die in faith of the promiſe: becauſe I am taken away ſhall I think the promiſe ſhall be of no effect? no; God ſhall bring you to the land of your fathers. Now when God ſhall caſt you on your ſick beds can you ſay, Behold I die; but go you on, God will make good his word, I die in faith that it ſhall go well with the Churches of God: there will be a time when they ſhall get the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, when Chriſt ſhall reign, and the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:121280:43"/> Saints ſhall be delivered from their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſours? Here was the ſpirit of Jacob: if you be ſuch a ſeed of Jacob you ſhall not ſeek Gods face in vain.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, it is not in vain for ſome men to ſeek God, but I am a poor wretched creature, and it may be in vain for me to ſeek the Lord.</p>
            <p>That place in the Pſalme fully anſwers any objection againſt our poverty, or the poverty of our prayers, Pſalm. 102.17. <hi>He will regard the prayer of the desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, and will not deſpiſe their prayers.</hi> The prayer of the deſtitute, the word ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifies a poore ſhrub in the wilderneſſe, a contemptible ſhrub, that is trodden on by the feet of beaſts, and none regards it; God regards ſuch prayers.</p>
            <p>If I could make an excellent prayer it were ſomewhat: No, he doth not deſpiſe thy prayer. It may be thy prayer is ſuch as thou deſpiſeſt, and that others would deſpiſe, but God will not deſpiſe it.</p>
            <p>But this was ſpoken perhaps to ſome in thoſe times.</p>
            <p>Mark what follows; <hi>This ſhall be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:121280:44"/> for the generations to come.</hi> This Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, this promiſe of God, <hi>it is written for the generations to come. And the people that ſhall he created ſhall praiſe the Lord.</hi> We that were not made them, but were created ſince, let us praiſe the Lord for this Scripture, that God will regard the prayers of poore ſhrubs, and not deſpiſe them.</p>
            <p>But they are great things that I ſtand in need of, and it may be in vain for me to ſeek ſuch great things at Gods hands; perhaps if I did ſeek for ordinary things there might be hope, but I am to ſeek great things, mercies for the Church and for the Kingdome, and people of God; is it not in vain for ſuch a poore wretch as I to ſeek ſuch great things?</p>
            <p>We may think that the things we ſeek at Gods hands are too great for us to beg, but they are not too great for God to give. It is obſerved of Perilla, when A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander would have him ask a dowrie for his daughter; Alexander preſently promiſed him 50. tallents; it is too much ſaith he, 10. tallents are ſufficient; Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:121280:44"/> anſwered him, if it be too great for you to ask, it is not too great for me to give. God loves that his people ſhould ask great things of him: yea he loves that the pooreſt, and meaneſt of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould ask him great things; and there is a gracious promiſe for that, Jer. 33.3. <hi>Call unto me and I will anſwer thee, and ſhew thee great and mighty things that thou knoweſt not.</hi> This is a promiſe to every one of the ſeed of Jacob.</p>
            <p>But when I pray in the time of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and Gods hand is on me, will it not be in vain to ſeek him then?</p>
            <p>It is true; to neglect God in former times, and then to pray onely in afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is a dangerous condition: but this temptation comes upon ſuch as have ſought God before. I now you ſeek God, but this is in your affliction, and will God regard you now? I ſpeak it onely to comfort ſuch as are carefull to ſeek God in the time of their health: yet if thou have been negligent, it is poſſible that God ſhould regard thee in the time of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction. Jonah prayed, and ſaid, <hi>I prayed
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:121280:45"/> and cryed by reaſon of mine affliction to the Lord, and he heard me,</hi> Jonah 2.2.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe it be affliction for ſin: for ſo the objection may ariſe. It is true, if I did ſeek God in the time of affliction that God did ſend for tryall, it may be God would hear me: but ſuppoſe Gods hand be on me for ſin, will God hear my prayers?</p>
            <p>That one notable example of David may help the people of God againſt ſuch a temptation: Gods hand was on him for his ſin, when he fled before Abſolom, God threatned that warre ſhould not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from his houſe: yet David then prayed againſt that wicked politition, and counſellour, that the Lord would turn his counſell to folly; and God heard Davids prayer in his affliction that was for ſinne, <hi>And the Lord turned the counſell of Achitophel to folly.</hi> Let us not be diſcouraged though polititians work never ſo craftily; though Gods hand be on us, and we have conſcience accuſing us, and ſay, I this is for your ſins that God leaves you thus in the hands of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:121280:45"/> your enemies, that God gives them ſuch power; that they find ſuch favour with the Prince as they do, though this be for our ſinnes, yet let us ſeek to God to turn the counſell of Achitophel to folly. It ſhall not be, nor hath not been in vain, we have found it ſo, that in our affliction, and affliction for ſin, yet crying to God to turn the counſell of Achitophel to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, God hath done ſo graciouſly, and hath incouraged us more and more to cry unto him for that end.</p>
            <p>But what need I ſeek to God, God hath decreed and determined what he will do, what God intends to do, he hath decreed from eternity, therefore whether we pray or not it ſhall come to paſſe, if we do not pray it ſhall come to paſſe. If God have intended to deliver me out of a ſickneſſe, it ſhall be done whether I pray or no; and when any ones time is come they ſhall die; and ſo when the time of a Kingdome is come it ſhall be deſtroyed, and not till then; therefore what good can prayer do?</p>
            <p>Though I ſuppoſe you cannot but be
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:121280:46"/> ſatisfied, and think that this objection hath little weight, yet for anſwer, I will give you a Scripture or two, Pſalm. 2. <hi>I will declare the decree,</hi> The decree of God concerning the advancement of Chriſt in his reſurrection, and ſo of the ſucceſſe of the work of Chriſts mediati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>I will declare the decree, the Lord hath ſaid thou art my ſon this day have I begotten thee: Ask of me, and I will give thee the heathen for thine inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and the utmoſt parts of the earth for thy poſſeſſion.</hi> Gods giving of Chriſt the heathen for his inheritance, and the utmoſt parts of the earth for his poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; it was decreed of God, yet Chriſt muſt ask it of his Father notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods decree. And another text re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable is in the propheſie of Daniel, where the text ſaith Dan. 9.2. <hi>In the firſt yeare of his reign, I Daniel understood by books, the number of the years where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the word of the Lord came to Jeremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah the Prophet, that he would accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh</hi> 70. <hi>years in the deſolation of Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem. And I ſet my face unto the Lord God to ſeek by prayer and ſupplications.</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:121280:46"/> Mark, Daniel underſtood by books what God had determined, concerning Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem; what need Daniel go further, he knew Gods mind what he would do whether he did pray or no? but mark, verſ. 3. <hi>I ſet my face to ſeek the Lord.</hi> After he knew what God had decreed, and what he would do, and what he had promiſed. Now we know not Gods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree: but if we did certainly know the decree of God in ſhewing mercy to the Land, yet it could no way hinder us but encourage us to ſet our faces to ſeek the Lord, and to ſeek him more earneſtly: therefore that is a vain objection.</p>
            <p>Again, it is not in vain to ſeek the Lord, if we examine all we have had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready: though we have not all we would have, yet if we conſider the ſupporting mercies, the preventing mercies, and the guiding mercies that God hath granted us, we ſhall find that it is not in vain that we have ſought him. There are abundance of mercies that thou haſt had already. It is an evil thing to complain of Gods grace, when God hath beſtowed ſuch mercies.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:121280:47"/> thou thinkeſt thou haſt nothing, becauſe thou haſt not all thou wouldeſt have; as a froward child becauſe it hath not every thing to its mind caſts away all. God hath been exceeding gracious to us; other ſouls would have adored God, and have bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him with their faces to the ground, if they had had but the hundreth part of thoſe mercies that we have; yet becauſe we have not all we deſire we are ready to think it is in vain. O let us take heed of diſhonouring the grace of God.</p>
            <p>Again, further thou thinkeſt it is in vain, becauſe God ſometimes denies in granting, and grants in denying. Many times God grants that we pray for in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying it, and denies that we pray for in granting it: our denyals are grants to us. Wo to us, if all were granted to us that we pray for. Much good may be gotten out of Gods denyalls: and God denyes us to do us good, and to prepare us for mercies: therefore it is not in vain that thou haſt ſought God, becauſe it is not in vain that thou art denyed.</p>
            <p>But further, it may be God delights
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:121280:47"/> more in thy praying, then in thy praiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing voice, therefore though thou have not that thou haſt ſought for, give leave to God to delight in thee which way he pleaſeth. There is the praying, and the praiſing voice of Gods people, thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteſt that God ſhould hear thy praiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing voice, it may be God delights to hear thy praying voice, and is may he ſhould not if thou haddeſt what thou wouldeſt have. Saith God to the Church, <hi>Let me hear thy voice, for it is ſweet.</hi> There is no man that will think the King denies his petition, as long as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> King loves to reade it. If one preſent a petition to the King, he doth not ſay he will preſently do it: but if he reade it, and when he hath read it, calls for it again, and again, will any man think it in vain that he hath put up that petition? as long as the King hears it, and delights to reade it, it is not in vain. So, as long as God loves to heare thy voice, and to reade thy petition it is not in vain. As for thy praiſing voice, God ſhall have enough of that in heaven, but he ſhall have none
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:121280:48"/> of thy praying voice: therefore why ſhouldeſt thou not be willing that God ſhould have more of thy praying voice here? All that ever God ſhall have of thy praying voice it is in this world, and after a little time God ſhall never heare us pray more. Therefore let us be willing to go on, and continue in prayer, and not to wonder why God keeps us on in a way of praying, becauſe all the time that ever God ſhall have to delight him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the praying voice of his people it is in this world: and for our praiſing voice, we would fain ſpend all our dayes in praiſing God for his mercies, but that is reſerved for another world.</p>
            <p>Further, it may be Gods way to ſtay till he bring a great deal of mercy toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and not by bitts, and drops. As when men deal with great merchants, they expect not to have payments, by ſix pences or ſhillings or Crowns at once: but though there be two or three or ten pounds due, they ſtand not on that but ſtay for a greater ſumme. Now little tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that deal by retail, they take it in by
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:121280:48"/> pence, and little ſummes, Chriſtians that are to deal with God, they deal for great things, and there are great tranſactions between God and a gracious heart: therefore think not much that God ſtayes with a greater ſumme. For as God deals with the wicked in the way of juſtice, ſo he deals with godly men in a way of mercy. He lets wicked men go on a great while, he comes not to judgement for ſin, but ſtayes till all come together, till a great ſumme of wrath and judgement come together. So he deals with the ſaints he comes not with leſſe mercies, but he ſtayes till abundance come, and when Gods time is come mercies will come to the full indeed.</p>
            <p>Further, it may be God hath ſo much mercy that thou haſt not a veſſell capable of it. Onely know that heaven, and earth and all are working for thee. Is the plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the ſowing of the husbandman, and all the ſhowers in vain; becauſe the corn is not in the barn? we account it not ſo: ſo we muſt not account our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in vain, becauſe the thing is not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained we pray for.</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:121280:49"/>
            <p>There are many other anſwers: but the time is ſo much gone, I come briefly to the application.</p>
            <p>Firſt, if it be ſo, that God ſaith not to the feed of Jacob ſeek my face in vain: certainly there are great things for the Church, that we may build on God is to do in theſe latter dayes, Why? becauſe all the ſeed of Jacob ever ſince Jacobs time, have been ſeeking God, not onely for their own times but for the Church, to the end of the world; all their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are upon the fyle, and muſt be anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one day. O what a glorious harveſt will it be! bleſſed are they that ſhall live to partake of it. We have a little, but cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, there are glorious things for the Church; becauſe every prayer ſhall be anſwered.</p>
            <p>Secondly, you that are of the ſeed of Jacob know your honour, though you be never ſo poore otherwiſe, God hath given you that which makes you rich: you have the key of heaven, you may o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the treaſures in heaven, and it ſhall never be in vain. Gods people are ſuch
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:121280:49"/> as are exceeding honourable in the eyes of God, and in this regard that they have credit in heaven, that they ſhall never ſeek God in vain. Bathſheba ſaith to So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, 1 King. 2.20. <hi>I deſire one petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thee, I pray thee, ſay me not nay,</hi> It is tranſlated by ſome, <hi>Ne confundas faciam,</hi> confound not my face. Indeed, the denying of a petition, it is a diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and a confounding of the face: but God will not confound the faces of his people, he never ſaith to them, ſeek ye me in vain: they are honourable ones.</p>
            <p>Now as it is ſaid of their father Jacob, he prevailed as a prince with God: ſo it may be ſaid of the ſeed of Jacob, they prevaile as Princes with God, they can do great things with God; it may be they cannot do other things that vain ſpirits can do, but they can do much with God in prevailing.</p>
            <p>O, here ſee your priviledge, and your riches, all the prayers that you have made in your life time they are all trading in heaven, they are not loſt. If a man have ventured a ſtock abroad to the Indies,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:121280:50"/> and do not hear of it in a great while, he thinks it is loſt and gone: but if he hear certain news that all his ſtock is ſafe, and in the place where he would have it, and thoſe that are there faithfully im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove his ſtock, he is revived by this, it rejoyceth his ſpirit, and he can ſay bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God, I hope to be a rich man for all this. I ſay to thee be of good comfort thy ſtock is not loſt, it is trading in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and every prayer that thou haſt put up is there. We ſhould account our prayers as riches, as adventures ſent to heaven, and not as children that ſhoot arrows and do not mind them.</p>
            <p>And then learn this, it is a great pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge to have a praying friend, a pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing companion. Many of you love friends that are delightfull, of a cheerly nature, and merry; but are they praying ones: praying friends are the ſpeciall friends: becauſe prayer can prevail with God. To have a friend in the Court, that can ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any petition, we think it a privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; to have one great friend in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is a great priviledge. Many people
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:121280:50"/> when they lie on their ſick beds, they ſend to ſuch and ſuch to pray for them: why do they not ſend to their companions, that they did drink with, and ſwear with, to pray for them? O, they dare not. Here is enough to convince any mans conſcience, who are the beſt men, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they ſay.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe thy condition were thus, that thou diddeſt lie on thy death-bed, and thy life did depend upon the prayers of foure or five men. If God ſhould ſpeak thus from heaven, thou art at the brink of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, onely this favour thou ſhalt find; thou ſhalt have leave to chooſe where thou wilt foure or five men to pray for thee, and according as they pray ſo it ſhall be with thee; thou haſt liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to chooſe through the world whom thou wilt. I appeal, would a drunkard chooſe foure or five drunkards, or a ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer chooſe ſwearers, or unclean ones that they moſt delighted in all their life time? If all ſhould depend upon it thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not chooſe ſuch; therefore thou art convinced in thy conſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence, tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:121280:51"/> that thoſe are not precious in Gods eyes, (however thy luſt have prevailed) but that the other are better men, that are gracious and have more credit in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Learn to prize praying friends, that can prevail with God.</p>
            <p>And let us ſet the crown upon prayers head, in the mercies we have from God, in publick mercies, and private delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of friends; attribute it not to ſecond means, to fortune and chance, take heed of denying God his glory.</p>
            <p>It is a ſign of a carnall ſpirit, when God hath glorified himſelf in anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the prayers of his people, to attribute it to any other means.</p>
            <p>As I remember, I read of the Porphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian atheiſts, that followed the atheiſme of Porphirie, they darkned the work of God in delivering the children of Iſrael out of Egypt thorough the red ſea. They ſay that Moſes had learned of the Egy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptians, and they were great Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers: and Moſes knew when it would be a low tyde, and what conſtellations there would be at that time, and that
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:121280:51"/> the tyde would prove low then, more then ever in the age of man, and Moſes took the nick of time, and lead them through the ſea. Thus atheiſts would darken the works of God, and put them of to naturall cauſes. So I find it related of the old Prophet in Jeroboams time; Joſephus hath it related of him, he ſent to Jeroboam to ſtretch out his hand he tells us that this was by accident, he was wearied all the day long, and now he had the Palſie, and after it was reſtored again; that which was done by prayer, he would have it by naturall means.</p>
            <p>Juſt thus it is, when God hath ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnified his mercy to England, and wrought ſuch wonders yet many carnall atheiſticall ſpirits, ſay this was an acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentall thing, and the policie of ſuch men brought it to paſſe, they attribute all to naturall cauſes, it is a ſign of a wretched profane heart: For if God ever magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied prayer he hath done it in theſe dayes. There are 2 or 3 Scriptures that ſince the world began were never more magnified, then by Gods working at this day.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:121280:52"/>
            <p>One is in Exodus 13. In the thing wherein they dealt proudly, God was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove them. Never ſince the world began was that more fulfilled. A ſecond is that in the 10. Pſalme, <hi>The wicked are ſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the work of their own hands.</hi> If ever there were a fulfilling of that Scripture ſince the beginning of the world, it is at this day. A third is this in the text. <hi>I ſaid not to the ſeed of Jacob; ſeek ye my face in vain.</hi> God (as I ſaid) hath raiſed a ſpirit of prayer among the ſeed of Jacob more then ever any in the world knew; there was never the like ſpirit of prayer raiſed, nor never the like things done for prayer.</p>
            <p>And the Lord the rather honoured the ordinance of prayer now, becauſe men ſo diſhonoured it before and perſecuted it, that the people of God could not meet and aſſemble to faſt and pray, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently it was a conventicle, and they were perſecuted as factious people. Becauſe God ſaw this way deſpiſed, he hath ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured it, and the former, and the latter mercies that we have received, we are to
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:121280:52"/> attribute to the goodneſſe of God by prayer, they were obtained by prayer. Let us ſtill be incouraged to ſeek God for what we would have: for God hath ſaid, <hi>it is not in vain to ſeek his face.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are many of us now that can do little elſe: if God have delivered you from ſickneſſe, and other evils, know that God hath delivered you to pray, the leſſe you can do otherwiſe, the more you ſhould do in prayer. I have read of a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, Numa Pompylius, that he would never go about any thing but he would go to the temple and pray: you that are inſtruments intruſted with our lives, and liberties, you had need to pray much, go into your cloſets and ſanctifie all your thoughts and reſolutions by prayer, that your help and aſſiſtance may not be in vain to us. And all others had nee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to aſſiſt you in ſeeking God in prayer. This incouragement we have, that there is not any of us that ſeek God alone, but we joyn with thouſands: why ſhould our place be found empty? why ſhould not our prayers joyn with the reſt? We ſhall
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:121280:53"/> meet many prayers in heaven; the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of our forefathers; the prayers of thoſe that are dead and gone that did not live to enjoy the fruit of their prayers, yet when we pray for mercies our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers meet with theirs in heaven: therefore let us be incouraged to ſeek the Lord.</p>
            <p>And if mercies ſhould come, what a daunting would this be to our hearts, that mercies are come, but we have not ſought them? and if mercies come not, conſcience wil flie in our face that we have been ſenſuall, carnall creatures, &amp; it is for our neglect of ſeeking God, that God hath denyed us the mercies that we expected.</p>
            <p>And then it ſhould be a uſe of rebuke to thoſe that begin to ſeek God, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue not. O wretch, why haſt thou left? whether wilt thou go? Is it in vain to ſeeve the Lord? certainly thou wert ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver acquainted with God and his wayes; thou wilt find it a dreadfull change, when it ſhall appear that thou haſt left God the fountain of living water, and haſt ſought after vanity, &amp; forſaken thine own mercy.</p>
            <p>But the main of all ſhould have been
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:121280:53"/> for the applying of it to the preſent occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. The Lord hath made good his word this day, that he hath not ſaid, <hi>ſeek ye me in vain.</hi> This day teſtifies it to be true that they are great things that prayer hath done. I have heard many years ago by credible teſtimony, that on this fifth of November, when we had ſuch a great mercy ſo many years ago, that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day it was known, that a great many godly people in the city kept it in faſting and prayer, ſo as it was eminently known and delivered from hand to hand of them in the city at that time, and you know what God did.</p>
            <p>But what hath he done of late? If our fathers ſhould riſe out of their graves, and we ſhould tell them that now the high commiſſion (that they were ſo trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with) is down; that there ſhall be no more ſtar-chamber, that cutting off of ears is gone, they would wonder how this ſhould come to paſſe. And whereas Parliaments were wont to be ſnap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in ſunder, that this Parliament is to continue by as firm an Act
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:121280:54"/> as any thing in the land is made by. And for oppreſſours, all the Courts and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Chanceries, they are down, and gone, God hath extirpated them: they were firſt caſt out of the houſe, and now out of the kingdome. And though an army did riſe and ſeek to bring us into ſlavery, yet God hath given us victory (though ſome have ſuffered hardly) and brought the adverſaries very low to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render their towns, and caſtles and arms. And here we are to rejoyce in God, and to bleſſe him for all.</p>
            <p>If many of our anceſtours ſhould riſe, and heare what we ſpeak, how we hold up our hands and bleſſe God, with what hearts would they joyn in the praiſing of God, and wonder that ever ſuch things ſhould be done! Let not the grace of God be in vain, as God hath not ſaid to us, ſeek my face in vain.</p>
            <p>What uſe ſhall we make of it?</p>
            <p>Let us give him reall praiſe, and not onely come to repeat it, and tell God of it, but make his praiſe glorious, put a glory on it; and then we do it, when we
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:121280:54"/> make a right uſe of his mercies, when we receive not his mercies in vain.</p>
            <p>What is it to make uſe of the memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all we celebrate?</p>
            <p>Firſt, the remembrance of theſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies muſt humble us; that is a ſweet humbling; it is better to be melted by the beams of the Sunne, then by the ſcorching of the fire.</p>
            <p>You will ſay, humbled, for what?</p>
            <p>There are three things that we have cauſe to be humbled for, upon the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the mercy of God towards us,</p>
            <p>Firſt, the ſinne of unbelief, conſider, when we were ſtraitned at any time, when we heard ill news, that our armies fled, and came to danger, how our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits were down as if all were gone. Let us check our hearts, God rebuked us in a kindly manner, we might have had a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious rebuke.</p>
            <p>Secondly, be humbled for all our mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring and repining, and diſcontent, O we did not think that the warres would have held ſo long, and O what taxations
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:121280:55"/> are upon us, and all our eſtates are rent away! And how many are there that had rather that all the good that God hath done for his people ſince theſe times ſhould never have been done, then that they ſhould ſuffer in their outward e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates. Be rebuked for all your murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and repyning at ſuch difficulties as you have met with in the great cauſe of God.</p>
            <p>The third thing that this mercy ſhould make us humbled for, and look back to, is that if ever there have riſen this thought in any of our hearts, that it had been better for me if I had never appeared ſo much. I ſee how things are like to be, the enemy prevails and is like to overrun all: had it not been better that I had not ingaged my ſelf ſo much? that I had not appeared ſo much? are they not wiſer men that have kept them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves quiet and ſilent, and done as little as they could, nothing but what they have been forced to? And when the Kings party come, if they tax us, they can do no more then force us. If thou have ſuch a
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:121280:55"/> thought, pray to God to forgive that thought: Let this that God hath done re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke thee. Art thou ſorry for what thou haſt done? thou ſeeſt God will do it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thee. If thou have been a publick in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, and haſt done good and yet if in fear of ſucceſſe thou haſt repented; God rebukes thee this day.</p>
            <p>Then labour to love prayer as long as you live, as David ſaith, <hi>I will call upon God as long as ever I live.</hi> Prayer caſts the ſcals, and hath the advantage.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the other ſide they feared not to ſuffer much if they were overcome; they think they have a head and they would be where he was, and he would counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance them, and make good their condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for them, but this ſide if they had been overcome, they had been men utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly undone: what a mighty advantage was there one way more then another?</p>
            <p>Then the Kings ſide if he had prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he had places of dignity to beſtow; if the Parliaments ſide prevail, we are but where we were, we do but maintain our own, we cannot expect to raiſe
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:121280:56"/> our condition. But how many broken Gentry expected to raiſe their condition on the other ſide? As it is ſaid concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Pope, and the generall Counſell; the Pope prevailed, notwithſtanding the generall Councell, though that were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove him, why? the Pope had Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallſhips, and Deaneries to beſtow but the Councell had none; they had the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage that way.</p>
            <p>Again, thoſe that appeared on the one ſide how were they diſcouraged extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily? on the other ſide they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to the utmoſt. On the one ſide how unfaithfull have they been? on the other ſide they have kept to their princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, becauſe their principles are ſuitable to the fleſh: but there are many on this ſide that have not gracious principles and had a publick cauſe, therefore they have been unfaithfull. We have uſe of men that have not principles to act by, but all the other go according to their own prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. The one part acts that they may gratifie mens luſts; now the generality of the world love it; they know if the one
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:121280:56"/> partie prevail they ſhall have liberty, and live lycenſciouſly, but if the other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail they ſhall live under laws. Now men would have their luſts; therefore when they ſee on the one ſide they ſhall have their luſts, and on the other ſide they ſhall be more curbed, they ſtrive hard for their luſts.</p>
            <p>At the firſt I wondred that men ſhould be ſo vile to fight to make themſelves ſlaves: but when I conſidered, they ſhall have ſlaves under them, and have their luſts, and the other ſide be more curbed, then I was ſatisfied, and wondered that God ſhould caſt the ſcales the other way, they having all the advantages in a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall way more then the other. Only here it is, we have people that have prayed, and this hath caſt the ſcale. Love prayer, and praying people, and joyn with them, be on their ſide, for God is with them, and will not ſuffer them to pray in vain: a praying Chriſtian is a uſefull Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an in the world.</p>
            <p>Again, make this uſe of all that hath been done. Look how far thou thinkeſt
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:121280:57"/> the adverſaries would have been hardned if they had prevailed againſt the cauſe of God, be thou ſo much the more reſolute in the cauſe of God. If they had prevailed how would they have blaſphemed? and many thouſands of Atheiſts would have been made more then there was before: what a mighty offence, and ſtumbling block would this have been? Now ſince God hath turned it the other way, juſtifie God and his cauſe; ſettle your hearts in the love of God, and his cauſe, and ſettle your ſelves more ſtrongly in the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in hand.</p>
            <p>Further, let us give him reall praiſe, that we may not receive the grace of God in vain. By this grace we hope that he hath given us our eſtates that we were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid would have been rent from us; we have the continuance of our liberties, and of the Goſpel. Let our hearts be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to God to give up our eſtates this day; let us renew our ingagements to God in ſecret, between God and our ſouls. Lord thou mighteſt have taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way my eſtate by the ſpoylers, it was
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:121280:57"/> near it; and thou haſt done it to other of my brethren, and is mine continued! that eſtate that ſhould have been ſpent for their luſts, I am reſolved to ſpend it in thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice that haſt preſerved it; and I account it a great mercy that I have an eſtate to honour thy name, I feared I ſhould not.</p>
            <p>God expects, that ever henceforward you make a more holy uſe of your eſtates then before. And call your hearts to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, what do I do with my eſtate for God? what honour hath God from my eſtate more then before? God expects more, or elſe God may juſtly ſay, in vain have I preſerved this wretches eſtate: there are many of my ſervants, if I had preſerved their eſtates, they would have improved them in the towns and places they lived in, and here is a wretch I have preſerved his eſtate, and he is more greedy and ſcrapes up for himſelf, and all his thought is, how to repair what he hath loſt by taxations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Lord may repent of what he hath done, and the curſe of God may follow ſuch a mans eſtate. Take
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:121280:58"/> heed, know that there is an ingagement after this time.</p>
            <p>And ſo for the liberty of the Goſpel, God expects that you ſhould prize the Goſpel more then ever. Lord, we were afraid the Goſpel would have been gone if thou hadſt given us up into the hands of our enemies, and our eyes ſhould not have ſeen their teachers; we ſhould not have heard things that refreſh our hearts; ſhall we have the Goſpel, and hope that our poſterity ſhall have it? we hope that we ſhall never provoke thee as we have done heretofore to take it away. A man that hath been in danger to looſe his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and hath recovered it will be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full after. Our ſlighting of the Goſpel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we had it ſo ordinary might have cauſed God to take it from us; and hath God reſtored it? let us take heed we provoke not God now, but attend upon the word more then ever we did.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, doth God ſay to us we ſhall not ſeek him in vain? Let not God call to us in vain. If when we ſeek God, our ſeeking is not in vain, then when God
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:121280:58"/> ſeeks us, let it not be in vain. There is all the reaſon for it in the world. If God be ſo gracious to poor baſe worms, ſinfull creatures, that if we do but chatter, our prayers are not in vain: is it not reaſon when God calls, that he ſhould not call in vain? When God calls out of his word to perform ſuch, and ſuch duties, God ſeeks thee, then make uſe of this text, I have called upon God, and I never called in vain; and now I go to heare the word, and out of the word he calls me, and ſeeks me, let him not ſeek in vain, but ſay, Lord what ſayeſt thou to thy ſervant? The Lord is ready to heare your cry, be you ready to heare his, and go on, go on with incouragement, the Lord hath incouraged us this day. And let all your prayers and indeavours break through all difficulties, and the Lords mercy ſhall break through all oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: for <hi>he hath not ſaid to the ſeed of Jacob, Seek ye me in vain.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:121280:59"/>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:121280:59"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalme 16.3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>But to the Saints that are in the earth, and to the excellent in whom is all my delight.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the beginning of this Pſalme David prayes to God for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, and for deliverancc out of ſome great evil, that it ſeems was upon him, or that he was in danger of. The argument that he uſeth, is, Firſt his truſt in God, <hi>In thee do I put my trust.</hi> And it was not an ungrounded and unwarranted truſt, but that which proceeded from his intereſt he had in God, <hi>O my ſoul, thou haſt ſaid unto the Lord, thou art my Lord:</hi> thou art mine. But what if David ſhould now periſh in his diſtreſſe, ſhould God be any loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer by it? David ſeems to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge this, that though he ſhould not be preſerved, yet God was bound to preſerve his own name, and his own cauſe; my goodneſſe extendeth not to thee. Though I ſhould live, yet it is little
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:121280:60"/> that I could do for thee. <hi>But to the ſaints that are in the earth.</hi> Though my good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe extend not to thee, yet I may be uſefull to thy people, unto thy Saints while I live, it extends to them, and they are they that my ſoul cloſeth with. O, I deſire to live, and to be preſerved that I may be of uſe to them.</p>
            <p>It is a great argument to prevail with God, when any of you are in danger, and ſeek for preſervation, if your hearts work thus to God, that the deſire you have to be preſerved is, that whatever you are, and what ever you can do may extend to the Saints, that you may live to be of uſe and ſervice in the world to Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Many of you when you apprehend your ſelves to be in danger, you cry to God to be preſerved: but to what end? wherefore would you be preſerved? wherefore would you live? If we may judge of your ends according to your pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe you would live that you may have more time to ſatisfie your luſts, that you may have more time to diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour God, that you may have more
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:121280:60"/> time to do miſchief in the places where you live. There is this in the heart, and God ſees it: God ſees whatſoever will be after in your lives; God ſees be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what was in your hearts when you cryed to be preſerved. But now one that is gracious he deſires therefore to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, O that I might live to be of uſe in the place where God hath ſet me. If God ſhould take me away now my conſcience tells me that it is little ſervice that I have done for him. I have been of little uſe in the place where God hath ſet me, O that I might be preſerved for this end, that what I am, or have, might extend to the <hi>Saints in earth, even the excellent in whom is all my delight.</hi> Thus you have the ſcope of the words, and the depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of them. And in them there are theſe two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the high eſteem of the Saints, they are <hi>the excellent of the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſecondly, the ſweet delight that Davids heart had in them, <hi>in whom is all my delight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt, the high eſteem that Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:121280:61"/> had of the Saints, and that Saints that were on earth, the excellent. The point is this, that
<q>The Saints of God, thoſe that are godly, are the excellent in the earth.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Then ſecondly, from this that he ſaith, <hi>in whom is all my delight.</hi> Obſerve this that,
<q>A gracious heart takes the moſt contentment in the Saints of God; he is much delighted in them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt is but a preparation to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond: therefore I ſhall paſſe it over brie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly. <hi>They are the excellent in the earth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> therefore my delight is in them.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>They are the excellent in the earth.</q>
            <p>Let them be what they will in regard of their outward meanneſs, yet there is an excellency in them. Job ſcraping upon the dunghill; and Jeremy ſticking in the mire in the dungeon, yet they had more glory and beauty upon them, then the great ones of the earth when they ſate upon their thrones. Though they <hi>lie among the pots</hi> (as the Pſalmiſt ſaith) yet are they as Doves, their wings are the wings of
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:121280:61"/> Doves, <hi>whoſe feathers are of gold, and ſilver;</hi> Pſal. 77.13. beautifull and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious. You know the judgement that the holy Ghoſt paſſeth upon the Saints in old time, that were outwardly mean enough<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there was as much meanneſs on them as the malice of the world could put: the text ſaith, <hi>they had tryalls of mockings, of ſcourgings, of bonds, and impriſonments, they were ſawen aſſunder, they were tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted, they wandred in ſheepskin, and goats skins: destitute, aflicted, tormented.</hi> What kind of creatures were theſe, ſurely they were ſome wretched men, and women that were thus hunted up and down to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in ſheeps-skins and goats-skins, deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute afflicted and tormented? No ſuch matter, they were ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch <hi>of whom the world was not worthy:</hi> v. 38. that is the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the holy Ghoſt upon ſuch, <hi>the world was not worthy of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The men of the world would have thought, &amp; did think that they were ſuch as were not worthy to live in the world: but the judgement of the holy Ghoſt was ſuch, <hi>that the world was not worthy</hi>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:121280:62"/> of them. I remember Chryſoſtome hath this interpretation of the phraſe, they are ſuch as are worth more then all the world, more then many thouſands of the world; one of them is worth more then all the men of the world beſides. It is a truth ſo; one Saint of God, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo mean, one poor youth, one ſervant that is truly gracious, is worth more then all the men of the world beſides that are not ſo. All the Monarchs and Princes on earth, have not that excellency in them that one poor child or ſervant hath that is gracious.</p>
            <p>But the ordinary interpretation is thus, they are ſuch as have that excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, as that the world is not worthy to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy them, they are not worthy of their preſence, that they ſhould ſo much as live among them; they are rather fit to be ſet as ſtars in heaven, and be before the Lord in his glory: the world is not worthy of them.</p>
            <p>But what is there in the Saints that makes them the excellent in the earth? <hi>The Saints that are the excellent.</hi> The
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:121280:62"/> word in the originall ſignifies the magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent ones; thoſe that have magnificent ſpirits, and are exceeding glorious.</p>
            <p>There is this in them (that I may briefly paſſe over this firſt.)</p>
            <p>They have the image of God upon, them, and therefore they muſt needs be the excellent on earth. The image of God makes them to reſemble God in that which the creature is able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of; That which is the height of Gods excellency: though it be true, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is in God is God himſelf: yet we conceiving of God according to our man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, there is ſomething of God that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears moſt excellent, and glorious. And it muſt needs be in regard of that expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, becauſe grace is called the image of God. Now when we draw the image of a thing, we draw it as near as we can ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that which is the moſt proper excellency of that thing. If I would draw the image of a man I do not draw the likeneſſe of a piece of fleſh, a beaſt hath that as well as a man, or I do not draw feet or leggs or the back parts of a man:
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:121280:63"/> but when the image of a man is drawn, there is his face drawn that is the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenteſt part, and there we endeavour to expreſſe his life, and ſpirit as much as can be: that is the moſt excellent part; and though the ſpirit cannot be drawn, there can be no picture of it; yet becauſe it is ſhewen moſt in the face, that is as near as we can go that is drawn there.</p>
            <p>So the image of God, is that wherein the creature reſembles God in height of excellency, and glory. It is not every re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of God that is Gods image: there are ſome things that ſet out ſome of the glory of God, and they are but called Gods footſteps, or his back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parts. All the reſemblance of God in his creatures; and the expreſſions of the power, and wiſedome; the inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things of God that we ſee in the creature, they are all but his footſteps, and backparts; they are not his image, Why? becauſe they do not reſemble God in that which he hath ſet out to us to be the height of his glory. What is that? The holineſſe of God that is the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:121280:63"/> height of his excellency. Therefore it is ſaid of God himſelf, <hi>holy and reverend is his name.</hi> Gods name comes to be reverend, by holineſſe: were it not for his holineſſe, notwithſtanding all the reſt, (if it were poſſible to ſeparate them) his name would not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend. Therefore when the ſaints in heaven glorifie God for his chiefeſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency it is thus <hi>holy, holy, holy.</hi> We finde not in Scripture any of Gods Attributes thrice repeated, Wiſe, Wiſe, Wiſe, or Almighty, Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Almighty, but <hi>holy, holy, holy,</hi> becauſe the excellency of God conſiſts chiefly in that.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe where grace is in the creature, reſembling this holineſſe of God, there is that principle whereby the creature is able to act as God himſelf acts: for that is holineſſe, the working of God to his own end in all things ſutable to his nature: ſo when the creature works to God as his laſt end, and in ſome meaſure is ſuteable to that God with which the creature
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:121280:64"/> hath to do, here is the Image of God.</p>
            <p>Therefore the ſcripture expreſſeth grace by theſe 4. things, as
<list>
                  <item>The image of God,</item>
                  <item>The life of God,</item>
                  <item>The glory of God, and</item>
                  <item>The Divine nature.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>There are theſe 4. expreſſions for the work of grace.</p>
            <p>The image of God, it reſembles God in his excellency. The life of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, Epheſ. 4: <hi>alienated from the life of God,</hi> that notes acting like God himſelf. And then it is the glory of God himſelf; and the divine nature, Rom. 3.23. 2. Pet. 1.3. So that there muſt needs be excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency in the Saints that have grace that is of this nature.</p>
            <p>Certainly, there is more of God in the meaneſt Saint, in the meaneſt gracious man or woman; there is more of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God then in all the world beſides<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then in heaven and earth. Take all the creatures<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all the glory of God in the heavens in the Sunne, Moon, and Starres, and put all into one. Take all the glory
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:121280:64"/> of God the ſeas, thoſe vaſt oceans, and put that into one; take all the glory of God that appears in the earth, all the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the earth, and all arts and ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and what you will; put all into one and the meaneſt youth or ſervant that hath the leaſt degree of grace, hath more of the glory of God then all this is. There is more of the ſhining of God in the leaſt degree of grace in the pooreſt Chriſtian in the world, then there is in all theſe creatures. If there were a quint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſence of all the excellency, and glory, extracted, and drawn, and put into one, yet there were not ſo much of God, God could not ſee ſo much of himſelf in that one creature that ſhould have the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of all creatures put together, as he ſees in the meaneſt Saint that hath the work of grace. And ſurely then they are the are the excellent of the earth if there be ſo much of God in them.</p>
            <p>The work of grace it is that which hath moſt of God; and whereſoever it is, it is that which is the proper work of Gods eternall love, it is a beam of it,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:121280:65"/> therefore there is a great deal of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency in it. Take all other creatures, and it is poſſible to enjoy all the good that is in all the creatures in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth (excepting this onely, the grace of God) through the bounty of God, and the pleaſure of God. There is nothing that the creature hath, but may be communicated as a fruit of Gods generall bounty except ſpirituall bleſſings in Chriſt: but where ever this is, though in the leaſt degree, it is of that nature, that it cannot come but onely from the eternall election of God. It is that which is the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Eternall life, whereſoever it is, it is that which will grow up to eternall glory.</p>
            <p>All common gifts will never grow up to glory, though they grow up to the height of glory, but the grace of God, true grace, it is of the ſame nature with eternall glory. Therefore for the kind of it, it is the greateſt good that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver God did, or that ever he will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate to any creature for all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:121280:65"/> I ſay, where-ever God hath municated any dramme of grace, that is the greateſt good that ever God did, or ever will communicate to all eternity, to any of his creatures, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is exceeding excellent.</p>
            <p>Onely excepting the work of God in the hypoſtaticall union of the two natures, wherein he joyned the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, and the divine nature together in one perſon; excepting that, the worke of grace in any ſoul is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt work that ever God did from all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, or that ever he will do, for the kind of it.</p>
            <p>Now that which hath ſo much of God in it, and comes from the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall election and love of God; and is the greateſt work that ever was done, or ever ſhall be done; and the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt good that ever was, or ſhall be communicated to any creature for ever, truly this muſt needs be the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt excellency. For God made the world for that end, that he might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate his excellency, and glory to the
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:121280:66"/> world, to the creature. Now that which was the greateſt thing that God intended from all eternity; for the communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of all his glory, it muſt needs make the creature excellent. That is the firſt thing, they are the excellent on earth in regard of the image of God upon them, the work of grace.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, tkey are the excellent of the earth, in regard of the ſeperating of them for God: they are thoſe that God ſet his thoughts upon from all eternity, that they might enjoy him. The great counſels that God wrought from all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, eſpecially were ſet on work up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this great thing of ſeparating of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain creatures for himſelf from the reſt of the world. Now when God ſhall ſet as it were (to ſpeak after the manner of men) his thoughts and counſels on work from all eternity to ſet apart a few creatures for himſelf; if there can be known who they are certainly, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but look on them as the excellent on earth: Now whereſoever we ſee the work of grace in any, we may by that know
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:121280:66"/> that theſe God hath ſeparated for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as ſetting his infinite wiſedome on work from all eternity above that. That was the thing he was moſt excerciſed in before the world, about the work of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parating ſuch and ſuch for himſelf. The Pſalmiſt ſaith, Pſalm. 4.3. that God hath ſet apart the godly for himſelf, they are thoſe that are dedicated, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to God; therefore there is a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull excellency put upon them.</p>
            <p>As you know any thing that is dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated and conſecrated, though it be never ſo mean in it ſelf, yet being once dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, being once made a conſecrated thing, there is a great deal of excellency put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that thing. As in the law, if it were but a piece of wood in the Tabernacle, if it were but a Badgers skin; if it were but braſſe or Goats hair or any ſuch thing that were meant in it ſelf, yet if it were once conſecrated and made holy to God, they looked upon it as having a great deal of excellency on it. Now I reaſon thus; if a piece of wood, or a little hair, or leather conſecrated to God had an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency:
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:121280:67"/> what then hath an immortall ſoul that hath the graces of the ſpirit, as ſo many pearls in it, when that is conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated and ſet apart to God to the glory and praiſe of his grace to all eternity; here muſt needs be much excellency.</p>
            <p>When a thing is conſecrated we look on it no more according to the quality of the thing, but to the conſecration. As I remember I read of ſome people in India, that when they have but loſt an Apes tooth that was conſecrated to their god, they will give an unſpeakable ſumme of money for the redemption of it again, becauſe it was a thing that was conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their god. So I reade of another that being raiſed from a mean birth, he took this way to make himſelf to be highly eſteemed of the people, he had a golden baſon that he uſed to waſh his feet in, he took that and made an idoll of it, and conſecrated it, and then every one fell down, and worſhiped it when it was conſecrated. Nay, ſaith he, if this which was mean before it was ſet apart to this uſe, comes ſo to be honoured, then I that
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:121280:67"/> am mean by birth, being ſet apart to the government, may as well be honoured by you. Thus then if the ſuperſtition, and will of man having conſecrated a thing, thinks he puts ſo much excellency on it, how much more when God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and the great and ſpeciall work of the holy Ghoſt that he is deſigned to, it is a ſpeciall work of his office to conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate ſouls to God, and to ſet them apart to himſelf, what an excellency muſt this needs be that is put upon them? <hi>They are the excellent of the earth.</hi> That is the ſecond.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, if we conſider that relation that the ſaints have to God; they are the neareſt relations that can be expreſt. Of children to parents, they are the children of God. Of a ſpouſe to her husband, they are the ſpouſe of Jeſus Chriſt, the ſecond perſon in Trinity; and in that regard they are more nearly united to God then the Angels themſelves are, in being the ſpouſe of the Son of God; yea the very members of his body, they have a nearer relation in that reſpect to the divine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:121280:68"/> to the ſecond perſon in Trinity then the Angels themſelves: for they have not ſuch a relation as this, therefore they are <hi>the excellent of the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, fourthly, if we conſider the great priviledges that the ſaints have, we ſhall ſee them the excellent of the earth. Not to ſpeak of their deliverance from ſin and guiltineſſe, and thoſe immunities that they have from others. But conſider they have this priviledge, that God in all his attributes and works, he is continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly working for their good. There is this excellent prerogative of the ſaints, there is no attribute of God but it is continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally working good to every ſaint of God. There is no work of Gods providence, but it works alway, continually for their good. It would be a mighty excellent ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour put upon any man, if but ſuch an honourable aſſembly as the Parliament, ſhould take thought for ſuch an one, and all their purpoſes and plots, and councels all the time they are ſitting ſhould tend to the good of ſuch an one in particular, taking notice in particular of him. It is
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:121280:68"/> that which I ſaid, all your wiſdome, and power and mercy, and faithfulneſſe, and the infinite alſufficiency of God is conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually every moment working, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the good of thoſe that love God in generall, but for every particular ſaint of God. God takes ſpeciall notice of them, and ſets all his attributes continually on work for their good.</p>
            <p>And the heavens continually work for them. They have this priviledge, that the whole world is made for them, God hath given them the world, they are the heirs of the world; as it is ſaid of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, he was the heir of the world, Rom. 4.14. Abraham had little himſelf, yet he had the world. Now the children in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit their fathers eſtate; if the world were Abrahams inheritance, then it is the inheritance of every child of Abraham: for ſo the children of Abraham are heirs to all that Abraham had, that is, as far as concerns them, therefore they that are his heirs are heirs likewiſe of the world, So the Apoſtle ſaith, 2 Cor. 3.18. <hi>All are yours, and you are Christs, and Chriſt
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:121280:69"/> is Gods.</hi> So that God, and the creatures are theirs, here is a mighty priviledge.</p>
            <p>Again, the priviledges that they have in all the good of the Covenant of grace. Whatſoever good there is in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace, all the rich promiſes in the Covenant of grace are the priviledges of the godly. It is admirable priviledges that the precious promiſes in Scripture ſpeak of to have intereſt in them all.</p>
            <p>Beſides, not onely the promiſes, btu the immunities that come from the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of grace, as this; that they are not to ſtand or fall for their eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall eſtate, by any thing that they are able to do themſelves, they are freed from this, their eternall eſtate hangs not on that which they can do. Whereas others, that are not ſaints, that are not in the Covenant of grace, their eternall eſtate hangs on their endeavours, and actions, God dealing with them according to the Covenant of works, being in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: though they may be ſuch as may after come to be ſaints, and as God hath elected, and in love may look on them as
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:121280:69"/> he intends towards them: but for the preſent they are in ſuch a condition, as that they know not, but that their eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall eſtate depends on that which they do themſelves. Now to be delivered from this, to have this immunity that ſuch a thing of ſuch a conſequence, as our eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall eſtate ſhould depend upon a ſure foundation, upon that which is done by Chriſt, and done already; it is an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite priviledge. Others cannot challenge to themſelves this priviledge, that God will accept of their endeavours; do what they can, yet not being in the Covenant of grace, thoſe indeavours are not acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted. That it pleaſeth God to accept the will for the deed; it is one of the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the ſaints, that comes by the Covenant of grace: but it belongs not to others, they have not to do with this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity and priviledge. So I might name divers others, but then I ſhould go out too far.</p>
            <p>Again, this is a glorious priviledge of acceſſe to the throne of grace, to come to God in prayer. God gives them the key
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:121280:70"/> of all his treaſures to come, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen them, and take what they will; it is a glorious privilege that belongs to the ſaints in any condition. God gives them a gracious praying heart, and that is the key of all the treaſures of God, of all the excellencies of God, that they have liberty to come and take out what they will, <hi>be it unto thee as thou wilt.</hi> Theſe <hi>are the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent of the earth,</hi> that have theſe pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges.</p>
            <p>Again, they are the excellent in earth in regard of that which comes from them. As the work of grace is ſo excellent as hath been ſpoken of: ſo every gracious action that comes from a gracious heart there is a wondrous excellency in it. There is not any one gracious action, but it hath more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency then heaven and earth. Not onely grace it ſelf, but any action that comes from grace, hath more of God in it, and God more delights in it then in all other things in heaven or earth.</p>
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:121280:70"/>
            <p>It is an expreſſion of Luther, (though he were a great advancer of faith, yet he was alſo of holineſſe as well as of faith, therefore) ſpeaking of any gracious work of a godly man or woman, ſaith he, <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioſa &amp;c.</hi> it is more precious then hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth. And then he goes on with another expreſſion I had rather be able to perform any one gracious act, of the pooreſt woman, or maid; of the pooreſt Chriſtian that is, then to be able to do all that ever Alexander, or Julius Caeſar had done. The leaſt act that comes from faith, from a ſanctified heart, he had rather be able to do it, then to get all the victories of Julius Caeſar and Alexander: all their triumphs and trophies were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the leaſt breathing of the work of grace in thoſe that are godly, that which comes from them are exceeding excellent. Now I reaſon they muſt needs be excellent, that have ſuch excellent things come from them. As when there were ſuch excellent things came from the body of Paul, that had ſuch virtue in them, that noted that there was a great
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:121280:71"/> deal of excellency that God conferred upon that Apoſtle, and a gread deal of honour that was put upon him: So when there comes flowing ſuch precious li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, ſuch precious things from the ſaints, as any holy action is, it ſhews that there is a great deal of excellency in them.</p>
            <p>Which (by the way) ſhould teach us to abound in holy duties; though our actions as they are from us corrupted, we look on them as deſpicable, yet know that God looks on them as the moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious things in the world, any breathing of a gracious heart, therefore <hi>he deſpiſeth not the broken heart, nor the ſighing of a contrite ſpirit.</hi> Pſalm. 51. God can deſpiſe Monarchs, and Princes of the world: but God cannot deſpiſe a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken heart, nor any breathings from ti. Though thou mayeſt deſpiſe it thy ſelf, and look on it as deſpicable, the Lord cannot deſpiſe it: he ſees ſo much excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency in it, though it be mixed with thy corruptions; yet there is that remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of excellency in it, if there be but
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:121280:71"/> ſo much as may denominate it a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious act, it is a glorious thing in the eye of God.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, (to name no more) the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of the ſaints appears in this, the great uſe that they are of in the world. As eſpecially this is one thing that God attains in them his great aim and end in creating the whole world. Were it not for a few gracious men, and women, what glory ſhould God have in all the world? They are thoſe that hold up the glory of God in the world, by which God hath his glory actively; for that is it that God aims at. It is true God can force glory in ſpight of mens hearts, he will be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in ſpight of Devils: but God hath no active glory, but from gracious, godly people (I ſpeak of the inferiour world) it is onely the godly that God hath glory from. Therefore were it not for them God (in ſome kind) had made all the world for nothing. Now thoſe that are imployed in ſuch a great work, and are of this great uſe in the world, as to bring to God that which he made the world
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:121280:72"/> for, the main, and great end that he made heaven and earth for; certainly theſe are principall in Gods eſteem, and excellent. God can ſay I have my end in theſe: Take any town where there are but two or three that are godly, what glory hath God but of theſe? So for other places where hath God glory but for a few con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible ones? They are theſe that God glorifies in high and great ſervices: theſe are the lights of the world, the ſalt of the earth: they are theſe that are the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of the world whereſoever they are; they are theſe for whom the world con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth ſo as it doth. There is a notable expreſſion in Iſaiah, <hi>In that day ſhall Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael be the third with Egypt, and with Aſſyria, even a bleſſing in the middest of the Land,</hi> Iſaiah 19.24. Whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they are in a Kingdome, or a fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or a town, they are a bleſſing in that Kingdome, in that town, and in that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, Iſrael ſhall be a bleſſing in the middeſt of the Land. Theſe are they that are the excellent of the earth.</p>
            <p>I would now willingly be over this
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:121280:72"/> that I may come to the other, but onely there is a word or two of application. And that is</p>
            <p>Firſt, to ſhew what a vaſt difference there is between thoſe that are godly, and thoſe that are wicked. Many things I might ſhew that the Scripture expreſſeth of wicked ones in all their glory: let all the glory of the world be put upon them, yet the Scripture ſpeaks exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contemptuouſly of them. I muſt not not ſpend time in thoſe expreſſions, onely one, and that is in Daniel. <hi>In that day a vile perſon ſhall ariſe.</hi> Daniel 11.21. It is ſpoken (as moſt Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters carry it) of Antiochus Epiphanes, yet he is called a vile perſon, as the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt ſaith, <hi>In whoſe eyes a vile perſon is contemned,</hi> Pſalm. 15. Antiochus, there are three things obſerved of him, yet he is called a vile perſon. Firſt, he was a great enemy to many ſinnes. Secondly, when the Jews wrote to him, becauſe they feared his wrath, he being a perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor of the Jews; there were ſome that lived in Samaria that were Samaritans
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:121280:73"/> that wrote to him to deſire his favour, that were not their own ſelves Jews, but Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans: and Joſephus ſaith, they wrote to him, Antiochus the mighty God; they gave him this title of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. He was a great man on earth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted where he lived; among the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans, a mighty god; yet the Scripture calls him a vile perſon. And then his name Epiphanes, which is as much as il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious or glorious. He had that title of almighty God, and illuſtrious, and glorious, and yet he was a vile perſon. Thus it is, where God ſees not the work of grace.</p>
            <p>The conſideration of this might give us ſome hope that there will be a time wherein God will appear for his ſaints. It is not probable that God will alway ſuffer his Jewels to be trodden under feet in the world; that God will alway look upon ſuch as are excellent on earth, and ſee them ſo abuſed in the world, and ſo contemptible as they are; ſurely this will not be alwaies. God hath his time to make it manifeſt to the world, that they
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:121280:73"/> are the excellent of the earth. They are now Jewels, yet they are ſuch as are in the dirt, and ſo are deſpiſed and contemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: but there is a promiſe that <hi>they ſhall be as the ſtones of a crown, lifted up, as an enſign upon the Land.</hi> Zach. 9.16. As the ſtones of a Crown, God will lift them up and make them honourable. And there is another text which is very obſervable; for every one to take notice of Gods intention to make theſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ones famous on earth. <hi>The gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of Judah ſhall ſay in their heart, The inhabitants of Jeruſalem ſhall be my ſtrength.</hi> Zach. 12.5. There was a time when the governours of Judah deſpiſed thoſe that were gracious and godly; but God hath promiſed that the governours of Judah ſhall be convinced of their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and ſhall ſay in their hearts <hi>the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of Jeruſalem ſhall be my strength in the Lord of hoſts their God.</hi> However now through the calumnies of the world; however now through the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proches that are caſt upon the ſaints of God, it falls out many time, that even
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:121280:74"/> the governours of Judah deſpiſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn them, and ſay they are ſeduced peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that they are factious and turbulent, and ſo their hearts are againſt them, and hate, and abhorre them, and look upon them with ſuch an evil eye, as thoſe that they name puritans: yet there is a time promiſed when the governours of Judah ſhall ſay in their hearts the inhabitants of Jeruſalem are my ſtrength in the Lord of hoſts. O ye inhabitants of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, Gods Church and people, his ſanctified ones (for Jeruſalem typified the eſtate of Gods people under the Goſpel; Gods ſanctified ones under the Goſpel) ſhall be ſuch as the governours of Judah in their hearts ſhall ſay, My ſtreng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h is in them. I ſee they are my beſt ſubjects my chief ſtrength is in them, and they are of principall uſe for me, and my kingdome is upheld in peace for them, and there is the bleſſing of God on them, they ſhall be my ſtrength in the Lord of hoſts their God. Now I ſee God is their God, God hears their prayers, and hath done much for them, we are convinced
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:121280:74"/> of it. O this will be a bleſſed time, when it ſhall be that the governours of Judah ſhall ſay ſo. Bleſſed be God that they do ſay ſo in any meaſure, that the gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of Judah ſay at all of the inhabitants of Jeruſalem, of the godly, that their ſtrength is in them: that they may ſee thoſe that are the excellent of the earth, in any meaſure to be truly the excellent of the earth.</p>
            <p>It were a ruefull ſpectacle, and would draw tears of bloud, to ſee the excellent ones to have that uſage that they have had. But now to ſee thoſe excellent ones countenanced in a publick way, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in publick courts of Juſtice, it is glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, when the governours of Judah ſhall do it: and thus we are to pray for that it may be more and more.</p>
            <p>And to ſay no more, let us learn to honour them that God hath honoured: ſince they are excellent ones, and God hath put excellency upon them, do you ſo too, look on them according as God eſteems them. It is obſerved, that God in the time of the law did not require them
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:121280:75"/> to offer in ſacrifice, Lions and Eagles, thoſe brave creatures; but Lambs and Doves, mean creatures, he would have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in ſacrifice. So God doth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the brave ſpirits of the world that ſtrut it out, but if there be any that be gracious and godly though they be never ſo poore, and mean, as Lambs and Doves, God honours, and reſpects them, they are a ſacrifice to him; <hi>the broken heart is a ſacrifice to God.</hi> Therefore when God would lift up himſelf in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, he ſaith, <hi>He that dwells in the high and lofty place.</hi> What of him? he looks to <hi>thoſe that are of humble, and contrite hearts,</hi> As if there were no other object in the world worth looking upon, he looks onely to them. As a thing that is before ones eye that he prizeth, his eye is faſtned on that: ſo God looks on them as if they were the onely object to be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked at; therefore let them be looked at by us with reverence in our hearts: it is fit that we ſhould honour thoſe that God honours.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is obſerved in the meſſage
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:121280:75"/> of the king of Babylon to Hezekiah, 2 Chron. 32.31. When Hezekiah was ſick, and God had given him a ſign of his recovery that the ſunne did go backward: It was a wondrous honour that God put on him that the ſun ſhould go backward. The ambaſſadours of the king of Babylon came to congratulate with Hezekiah af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his recovery: but what was the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? not onely to congratulate with him for his recovery; but to enquire of the great miracle, ſo the text ſaith, <hi>the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours of the prince of Babylon were ſent unto him to enquire of the wonder that was done in the land;</hi> Why did they enquire of this wonder? there were many wonders done, but they were not ſent to enquire of others but of this. Becauſe they worſhiped the ſun for their god and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their god had put ſuch an honour upon Hezekiah; they perceived the alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſun that it went backward, and they enquired of the matter, concerning the alteration in the ſun, and after enquiry there was news that it was for the ſake of Hezekiah. Now becauſe they worſhiped,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:121280:76"/> the Sunne as their god, and ſo apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that their god had put ſuch an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour upon Hezekiah, they honoured him too. Though Hezekiah were king of the Jews, and they were enemies one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Jeruſalem, and Babylon, yet when God had honoured him, they ſent to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate one another, then they put ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hour and reſpect one upon another upon that occaſion.</p>
            <p>That ſhould teach us, if the heathens when they ſee their God put honour on any, they honour ſuch as God honours, then when you ſee or hear that God ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours gracious and godly men, and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men do you ſo too; prize them, let them have high eſteem in your hearts. You have heard this day what honour God puts upon his ſaints, therefore learn you to honour them. And much might be ſaid, to draw the hearts of all people to the love of the people of God. Somewhat for the people of God; to walk as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ones, not to defile one another. And for others, if they would be thoſe here in the world that be excellent and
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:121280:76"/> glorious; it is the outward things that you hang on you, clothes, and riches that make you excellent ones in the eye of God, but it is grace, and godlineſſe, by faith the fathers obtained good report. Some think there is no way to get eſteem but outward bravery, great livings, fine clothes and the like, and men eſteem that the way to be accounted eminent more then others. So there are many mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters that think to get eſteem if they be honoured before great ones, and go brave. But you know by experience, that a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full godly miniſter, that walks faithfully, and conſcionably, he gets more eſteem in the hearts and conſciences not onely of thoſe that are godly, but of thoſe that have enlightned conſciences then a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of thoſe; and they vex at it that they ſhould do ſo; Why? they go a way to work to get more eſteem, but they are deceived; they look at excellency where it is not. It is not ſuch things, but in the work of grace, that prevails with the conſciences of men. Boniface the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr when he was asked the queſtion,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:121280:77"/> if he might have the ſacrament, if he would drink it in a wooden challice? ſaith he, the time was that there were wooden cups and golden prieſts, but now there are golden cups and wooden prieſts. There was a time in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times, they were very mean, they were content with wooden veſſels; but the men were gold in regard of grace, and godlineſſe, and ſo they were highly eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; but now they have golden cups, that is a great deal of bravery and glory; but they have wooden prieſts, thoſe that have no true excellency in them. <hi>The heart of the wicked is little worth.</hi> It may be his eſtate, his houſes, his lands may be ſomewhat worth, but what is his heart worth? he hath nothing in himſelf to commend himſelf. But now the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Gods people is in that, it is in the ſoul and heart.</p>
            <p>It were an uncomfortable thing to any of you, if ſuppoſe you have a ſervant along with you where you go, and all the reſpect you have is for your ſervants ſake; if any entertain you into their
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:121280:77"/> houſe, it is not out of reſpect to you, but reſpect to your man; they love your man, and for his ſake they entertain you; this would deject your hearts if you ſhould know that you have no reſpect for any good in your ſelves, but for your ſervants ſake. So the men of the world, they have reſpect, but what is it for? for their riches, for their honour, for their brave clothes, for their money; all ſervants under them, they have no reſpect for any thing in themſelves, they have no ſpirituall excellency; eſpecially when they are to deal with God, and the conſciences of men they have no reſpect. But godly men have not ſo many ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to gain reſpect by outward things: but that reſpect they have of Gods ſaints, and in the conſciences of men they have it from an internall excellency. But we let this go.</p>
            <p>It follows the ſecond point, <hi>The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent of the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In whom is all my delight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is but little that can be done I ſee, though it were the point I intended moſt.
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:121280:78"/> That that hath been ſaid already makes way abundantly into the heart, that if they be the excellent of the earth, there is cauſe that we ſhould delight in them. That is the point, that
<q>A gracious heart takes great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the ſaints on earth.</q> Firſt in their perſons,</p>
            <p>Or elſe in their ſociety, and communion with them.</p>
            <p>Or rather thus; they take delight in them, ſeverally or joyntly.</p>
            <p>If they look upon any one ſaint of God, they have delight in him, but they have more to look on all together joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; ſo they can ſay their ſouls delight in them there is a ſweet complacency take them joyntly. And that is that which I ſhall ſpeak to at this time, the delight that is to be taken in the ſaints, took joyntly together. The delight in the ſaints in regard of the ſweetneſſe of their ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety and communion with them: for ſo this delight of David is to be taken in a large ſence, not onely in one particular, becauſe of the good that he ſaw in their
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:121280:78"/> perſons: but in regard of all the good he ſaw in them, and by them in joyning with them take them altogether joyntly. All the good that came from them, ſo he delighted in them. There is a great deal of delight and contentment to be had in the ſaints of God, eſpecially joyntly.</p>
            <p>If you look at one ſometimes (though in never ſo mean a condition) there is a great deal of delight there. As Doctor Tayler the Martyr, that we read of in the book of Martyrs coming to Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, he profeſſed that it countervailed all his trouble in priſon, that he was acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with that Angel of God John Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford meaning him in particular. And another that profeſſed that he had rather be with Cato, (a heathen) for his morall excellencies, in priſon then with Ceſar in the Senate in all his pomp. To be ſhut up with one godly man is a great deal of delight and contentment what a great deal of delight is there then in their being together, and in that way wherein moſt of their excellencies appear? ſuch delight is in them joyntly.</p>
            <pb n="144" facs="tcp:121280:79"/>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe the moſt comfortable communion that poſſible can be is enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with them, and in them: for</p>
            <p>Firſt, is it not a moſt delightfull thing to ſee a company of godly people toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to behold the reſplendent beauty, and glory of the graces of Gods ſpirit? If there were nothing elſe, what a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull thing is it ſaith the heart? The very ſight of good men it is pleaſing and delightfull, to thoſe that look upon their faces, wiſdome makes their faces ſhine. The ſeeing of the reſplendent grace of God in them is very delightfull. What is the delight of God, but the ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſhining of his glory in his works? eſpecially when God ſees that which is the ſhining of his higheſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as his own grace and holineſſe, that God delights in moſt. So when a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious heart ſees his own image, and that grace that God hath wrought in him, he ſees it reſplendently in others, it is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull object.</p>
            <p>Again, there is a comfortable commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with them in regard of the fragran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:121280:79"/> of grace. The beauty of grace is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull, but the fragrancie, the breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of grace, are ſweet in the heart. The beholding of it is delightfull to the eye, but the workings of their grace is excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſweet, and comfortable to the heart: Therefore ſaith the Church, <hi>Let my belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved go down into the gardens, among the beds of ſpices.</hi> Cant. 6.2. All the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of God in the world are as the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of Chriſt; and every particular Church in that garden is as a bed of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and every particular ſaint is as the ſeverall parts of that bed eſpecially the fragrant ſmell is very ſweet. It is ſaid of Alexander, his very body was of ſuch a conſtitution, that where ever he went there was a ſweet ſavour came from his body. Certainly, where there is but one of Gods Children, there it ſweetneſſe from him; but where there is a company joyntly, there is a wonderfull unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſweetneſſe comes from them; it is exceeding comfortable to a gracious hear.</p>
            <p>Again, their communion is comfortable
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:121280:80"/> and delightfull joyntly, in regard of the nearneſſe, there being no communion under heaven wherein there is that near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe one to another, as of the ſaints. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, (that you may ſee how near they come together, and are made one, and ſo are exceeding delightfull one to another) any thing the more ſpirituall they are, the more they are united; the more cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall they are, the leſſe union. A heap of ſtones are not united, as the ſeverall beams of the ſunne, a thouſand of them are united in one point, becauſe they are of a ſpirituall nature. So it is with the ſpirits of men, the more carnall any men, and any ſociety is, the leſſe union: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the reaſon why the people of God many times are divided, and not united is, becauſe they are carnall. <hi>Are ye not carnall,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, when there were diviſions? were you ſpirituall you would be more united one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>It is with ſpirituall ſociety in regard of ſpirtuall union, as it is with the ſoci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of wickedneſſe. There is bodily, fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:121280:80"/> wickedneſſe, and there is ſpirituall wickedneſſe. Now thoſe that joys toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in groſſe, bodily wickedneſſe, they are not ſo cloſely united as thoſe that joyn in ſpirituall wickedneſſe. A companion of drunkards or whoremongers, they take delight in one another, and joyn in wickedneſſe, but it is corporall, therefore they ſoon fall out, and fly in the faces one of another: but thoſe that joyn in ſpirituall wickedneſſe as politick ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men men that joyn in miſchief in a ſpirituall way, they keep mighty cloſe, and you cannot break their bond of u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; they will ſuffer much before they will diſcover one another, and break u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion one with another, becauſe their uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is in a way of ſpirituall wickedneſſe. So on the contrary, when any are united in the ſpirit of holineſſe, they are migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily united, there is no ſuch union under heaven is that.</p>
            <p>We read of the curtains of the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, Exod. 26. there were ſome of them that were made of purple, and ſcarlet, and fine linen, and their taches that held
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:121280:81"/> them together were pure gold. There were others of goats hair, and their buckles were braſſe. So it may ſet our the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent condition of men in the Church. There are ſome in the Church that are truly gracious and godly, that excell in grace, and they are united by tacks of gold, their union is mighty ſtrong and glorious in their hearts. There are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the Church, outward profeſſours that are carnall, that are goats hair goats in the Church; and they maintain a uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on too, but it is but braſſe, the ground and bottome of the union is but mean, it is not ſuch a golden union, as the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the hearts of Gods people; there are no people under heaven ſo uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as they.</p>
            <p>It is true, through their corruption there is a great deal of diſſention (as there is corruption in the beſt) but that is as farre as they are carnall; the more ſpirituall they grow, the more near is their union one to another, and the more entire is their love, <hi>My beloved is one,</hi> ſaith Chriſt to his Church, <hi>and the
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:121280:81"/> daughters ſaw her and bleſſed her.</hi> There is an oneneſſe, and intireneſſe in the hearts of the ſaints, and this makes them to be bleſſed by thoſe that behold them, and makes their communion very delightfull: That is the firſt particular, their commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is moſt delightfull of all other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munions: therefore David ſaith, <hi>all my delight is in them,</hi> taking them together.</p>
            <p>But then in the ſecond place, a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous heart muſt needs delight in the ſaints, if you take them joyntly; becauſe that when they are together, there God is worſhiped: the ſolemneſt worſhip that God hath is from the faints joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. As I told you before that the glory that God had in the world was from them all: but the ſolemnity of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip cannot be but from them joyntly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. Therefore the great delight of a gracious heart is to be with the ſaints when they are joyntly together: becauſe there the name of God is honoured, and they worſhip God in a ſolemne way; God is honoured among them.</p>
            <p>Chriſt himſelf much delights in the
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:121280:82"/> Saints when they are joyned together in in the duties of holy worſhip, do but compare two texts of Scripture, that will both make us in love with the ſaints, and delight in joynt communion with them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Compare Pſalm, 22.22. with Heb. 2.12. The Pſalme is a propheſie of Chriſt; and generally all interpreters go this way, that it is ſo, it appears by the Pſalme that Chriſt eſpecially is meant: the text ſaith <hi>I will declare thy name unto my brethren in the middeſt of the congregation will I praiſe thee.</hi> It is the promiſe of Chriſt to declare the name of his father to his Church and people, and in the middeſt of the congregation he ſhall praiſe God. Mark it, in Heb. 2.12. the Apoſtle ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies it to the ſaints joyned together, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>I will declare thy name unto my brethren, in the middest of the Church, will I ſing praiſe unto thee.</hi> This was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt had been in the fleſh, yet the Apoſtle applies this to the Church, <hi>in the middest of the Church, will I ſing praiſe unto thee.</hi> This they gather hence, that Chriſt he delights in being with his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:121280:82"/> when they are joyntly together, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the ſolemne worſhip of God, that is tendered to God by them, and he joynes with them in it as a delightfull work: as they are together to praiſe God, Chriſt is praiſing him; as they worſhip, Chriſt is worſhiping. Now every ſaint of God hath the ſpirit of Chriſt in him, and ſo he delights in the ſociety of the ſaints on this ground, becauſe there is worſhiping of God, and God is praiſed ſolemnly among them. If there be any in the world, wherein God hath ſolemne worſhip, it cannot but grieve a gracious heart, that he is not with them, his heart is with them, he delights to be with them, eſpecially in ſuch a work as that, it grieves him that he cannot be there.</p>
            <p>It is a note of an Interpreter that I have met with upon Iſaiah 6. where the Angles cry <hi>Holy, holy, holy, Lord of Hoſts,</hi> the Prophet cryes, <hi>Woe unto me for I am undone,</hi> &amp;c. ſaith he, upon this ground, becauſe he could not joyn with thoſe bleſſed creatures, and ſo magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:121280:83"/> and praiſe, and worſhip God; that he through his ſinfulneſſe was not able to joyn with them, he cryes, <hi>Woe is me, I am undone.</hi> So when any gracious heart doth but hear, that there is a people in the world that are precious ones, the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent on earth, that joyn in the worſhip of God, and honour God in his own way, and enjoy communion with God, and I cannot joyn with them, woe to me that there ſhould be any let or hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that I cannot come and joyn with them: for my heart is there, my delight is in the ſaints when they are joyntly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: becauſe Gods ſolemne worſhip is there.</p>
            <p>But thirdly, my delight is in the ſaints joyntly, in regard of the wonderfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light God hath in them. A gracious heart muſt needs delight in them, becauſe God himſelf takes ſo much delight in them: but eſpecially when they are joyntly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. There are ſpeciall expreſſions in Scripture of Gods taking delight in the ſains joyntly, as in Zephany, Zeph. 3.17. <hi>the Lord thy God in the middeſt of thee is
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:121280:83"/> mighty: he will ſave, he will rejoyce o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thee with joy: he will reſt in his love, he will joy over thee with ſinging.</hi> What expreſſions are here of Gods delighting in his people! <hi>The Lord thy God will rejoyce, he will rejoyce over thee with joy; he will love, he will reſt in his love, and joy, and joy over thee with ſinging.</hi> And in Iſaiah, you ſhall find that the Church is called Hephzebah, Gods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light: it is a wondrous delight that God hath in his ſaints.</p>
            <p>There are wonderfull expreſſions in Scripture for the manifeſting of Gods delight, even to admiration, eſpecially in the Church joyntly together. They are ſuch expreſſions as we could not think or invent: as namely, that he calls his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple his <hi>portion, his pleaſant portion,</hi> Deut. 32.9. God calls them <hi>his inheritance, the lot of his inheritance:</hi> Jer. 12.7. he calls them <hi>the dearly beloved of his ſoul;</hi> Exod. 19.5. he calls them <hi>his peculiar treaſure:</hi> God hath treaſures in the world; the creatures that are called the <hi>good treaſures of the Lord:</hi> Deut. 28. but
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:121280:84"/> this people are called his peculiar treaſure, there is a particularity: There is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kind of excellency in the people of Gods delight, then in all other creatures; they are his common treaſure, but his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are his peculiar treaſure. God calls them <hi>his glory, The houſe of his glory,</hi> Iſa. 46.13. <hi>The crown of his glory,</hi> Iſa. 60.7. he calls them the <hi>Throne of his glory,</hi> Iſa. 62.3. in ſeverall places that I cannot ſtand on. His glory, the Houſe of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the Crown of his glory, the Throne of his glory. He calls them the royall Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adem, he calls them his ornament, an ornament ſet in Majeſty and glory. There are theſe expreſſions, and more I might name of Gods delighting in his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Therefore if God delight in them and finde ſatisfaction, much more' ſhould we.</p>
            <p>Chriſt ſpeaks of his Church, <hi>O my ſister, my ſpouſe, my heart is raviſhed with thee.</hi> It is a ſtrange expreſſion, for Chriſt himſelf to be raviſhed with his people. It is an expreſſion beſeeming the Church, to have ſaid ſo to Chriſt, but
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:121280:84"/> for Chriſt to ſay ſo to the Church, it is wonderfull. And again, <hi>My love, my dove, my undefiled one,</hi> Cant. 2. and at that very time when the Church was in a ſtate of ſecurity, that Chriſt ſhould call her his love, his dove, his undefiled; all to expreſſe the abundance of delight in his people. Well, if God have ſuch delight in them, much more ſhould the ſaints.</p>
            <p>Again, if we conſider further, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God among his people, it is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other argument why the ſaints of God ſhould take ſo much delight in other ſaints, eſpecially when they are joyned together, becauſe God is preſent there. <hi>The Lord is here,</hi> is the name of all their aſſemblies, <hi>The Lord dwells, and hath his tabernacle in Sion.</hi> It is a ſtrange expreſſion concerning the preſence of God, in that he makes his people his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation. As the people of God call God their habitation: ſo God calls his Church his habitation. <hi>God dwels in Sion.</hi> Pſ. 90. Would you not delight to keep houſe with God? Where Gods people are, God keeps houſe; and we ſhould long to
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:121280:85"/> have it our own houſe, and not come as ſtrangers. A man may come as a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and take a bit, and be refreſhed in a family; but it is not his houſe. But now Gods people when they go toot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the ſaints they ſee God there, and they have that houſe for their houſe. It is called (as I told you) <hi>the houſe of his glory;</hi> that houſe that God deſires to dwell in; he hath a mighty love to that houſe, to dwell among his people. In Pſal. 132. there are many great and excellent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions. <hi>For the Lord hath choſen Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he hath deſired it for his habitation,</hi> Pſal. 132.13, 14. God deſires Zion; what is Zion, but onely his ſaints and people joyned together? Zion was a type of the Church: ſo now all the ſaints of God together are Zion. Now God hath a deſire to this habitation. God dwels in the high and holy place, the higheſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is Gods habitation; but though God have ſuch a houſe in heaven, yet he is not (as it were) contented with that houſe, but he deſires another houſe; he hath a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to Zion to be his habitation, and the
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:121280:85"/> houſe where his honour dwelleth. You know a Prince may have ſome houſes of meaner regard, when he goes to his ſport, he may have a mean houſe to lodge in for a while: but his pallace where he ſhews his Majeſtie, and honour, that is more glorious. So the people of God, and the Church, is called the houſe of Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, it is not a mean houſe, but a houſe of honour.</p>
            <p>Further, it is that houſe that he means to dwell in for ever, he loves it ſo well. This is my houſe, I will dwell in it for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. I am ſo well pleaſed with it, I will reſt in it for ever. Surely, we have cauſe to reſt our hearts in Gods people, when God finds reſt there, and for ever.</p>
            <p>It may be ſome of you are ſometimes acquainted with the people of God, and at the firſt delight in them: but your hearts being carnall you ſoon grow wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them. It is not ſo with God, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights in his people, and reſts there, and reſts there for ever,</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, how is God preſent with his ſaints more then in other places;
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:121280:86"/> why is God ſaid to dwell among his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, his Saints?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, in two regards God is ſaid to dwell among his people in a ſpeciall manner.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe he makes himſelf known to his people, more then to all the world beſides. There are none that know the counſell and mind of God, ſo as his ſaints do. <hi>God is known in Judah.</hi> Pſalm. 29.9. There God opens himſelf, <hi>In his Temple every man ſpeaks of his glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe God communicates himſelf moſt among his people. God is ſaid to be in heaven. Why? but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there he manifeſts his glory more then in other places; therefore heaven is his habitation. If that be his habitation where he manifeſts himſelf more, then his people are his habitation, becauſe he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſts himſelf moſt there.</p>
            <p>Secondly, heaven is the place of Gods reſidence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> becauſe he communicates him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf moſt there: then alſo Gods people are his reſidence, he communicates him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:121280:86"/> there. And he communicates himſelf to them in a ſpeciall manner in foure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He communicates more choiſe mercies.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He communicates mercies more fully.</p>
            <p n="3">3, He communicates mercies more po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfully.</p>
            <p n="4">4. More univerſally, then to others.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He communicates goodneſſe among his people and ſaints more choiſely, more choiſe mercies of God. There is a remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able place in the Pſalmes, <hi>The Lord that made heaven and earth bleſſe thee out of Zion.</hi> Pſal. 143. ult. He ſaith not the Lord that made heaven and earth bleſſe thee, either out of heaven or earth, but out of Zion, as noting that the choyſe mercies that God hath to communicate are out of Zion; among his people joyned together in the way of worſhip. Would you deſire that God ſhould bleſſe you with the chief mercies that he hath? look upon God as bleſſing out of Zion; out of Zion God communicates his choiſeſt mercies: therefore it concerns all to be in Zion, that they may have God to bleſſe them
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:121280:87"/> out of Zion; there runs the ſweeteſt of Gods mercies indeed in Zion.</p>
            <p>Again, God communicates his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies more fully among his people then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other way. Pſalm. 36.7, 8. <hi>How excellent is thy loving kindneſſe, O God! therefore the children of men put their truſt under the ſhadow of thy wings. They ſhall be abundantly ſatisfied with the fatneſſe of thy houſe, and thou ſhalt make them drink of the rivers of thy pleaſures.</hi> They ſhall be abundantly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied; how? not with the creatures, but with the fatneſſe of thy houſe. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with thy communication to them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. God hath abundance of mercies for his ſaints alone: but when they are among the ſaints joyntly together, then they ſhall be abundantly ſatisfied with the fatneſſe of his houſe, and he ſhall make them drink of his rivers of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. While they are alone in corners, they may have many ſweet drops of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure from God, but when they are joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the ſaints, there are rivers of pleaſure, and delight that come to their
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:121280:87"/> hearts: therefore there is great delight to be had in the ſaints of God when they are joyned together.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, he communicates them more powerfully, mark, in Pſalm. 13<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.3. <hi>As the dew that deſcended upon the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Zion; for there the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded a bleſſing, even life for evermore.</hi> There was bleſſing, and the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there went a powerfull work of Gods grace upon the hearts of people there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when they were joyned together in Zion: there God commanded the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. If you would have God ſpeaking powerfully to command a bleſſing on your ſouls you muſt be among his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, you muſt joyn in a holy fellowſhip with his people; there God commands it.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place, more univerſally all the goodneſſe of God is communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted among his people, therefore the Church is called <hi>the perfection of beauty;</hi> Pſalm. 50. that ſome tranſlate, the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality of excellency and beauty. There is a univerſality of all among the Church and people of God. And in another place,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:121280:88"/> 
               <hi>All my ſprings are in thee.</hi> Pſa. 87. ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of joyning with the people of God, that is, all my ſprings of truth that are revealed to me; all the ſprings of comfort that I have communicated to my ſoul, all the ſprings of grace that I have, to quicken me, they are all in thee in the joynt ſociety and communion with Gods people, I find all. Thus we ſee the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God among his people in regard of the communication of himſelf to them, and therefore what a great deal of cauſe there is to joy, and delight in the ſaints joyntly together.</p>
            <p>Again further, there is abundance of cauſe to delight in them joyned together, in regard of their admirable priviledges as they are joyned together. They have priviledges as they are alone, but as they are joyned they have committed to them the <hi>oracles of God,</hi> Rom. 3.2. all the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances by which God conveyes himſelf. To them are committed the ſeal of the covenant, you cannot ſingly have the ſeal of the covenant, but joyned with the people of God, cloſing with them. To
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:121280:88"/> them is committed the very power of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt: ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>When ye are together with the power of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.4. a glorious priviledge. Yea, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, take this one thing they are inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours to all the promiſes that ever God made to the Church from the beginning of the world. There is no ſociety of ſaints that joyn in Chriſtian fellowſhip, but they are ſo. See a remarkable place for that in Iſa. 54.17. <hi>No weapon that is formed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee ſhall proſper, and every tongue that ſhall riſe againſt thee in judgement thou ſhalt condemn: this is the inheritance of the ſervants of the Lord.</hi> That promiſe that God made to the Churches before, this is their heritage. And conceive of this one now that is of great uſe, that all that is ſaid in Scripture concerning Gods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to be among his people, and in Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, all were but to type out the excellent condition of Gods Church in the times of the Goſpel. The moſt of the expreſſions are of Gods delight among his people in the time of he law: but know that all thoſe expreſſions were but meer types, and there is a great deal more in
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:121280:89"/> the Antitype there in the type: therefore the ſaints of God joyned under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell have abundance more of the glory of God, of the preſence of God, and of priviledges, then Zion had, or Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem could have; becauſe that was but a type of their happy condition under the time of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>It is an obſervable place that we have in the Hebrews, it is ſaid concerning the ſtate of the Church, that <hi>the law had but a ſhadow of good things to come.</hi> Heb. 10.1 and not the very image of the things. It was not ſo much as an image: obſerve, a ſhadow is not ſo much as an image; but an image is not ſo much as the thing it ſelf: but that was not an image, but a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow. As a Painter that takes an image, he draws firſt the dark ſhadow with a cole, there is a great deal of difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween that ſhadow, and the image in beauty: ſo much difference there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween all the glory of God in the Church in the time of the law, and that glory of God that is among his people in the time of the Goſpel. We may ſafely ſay, there is
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:121280:89"/> the like difference between Gods mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſting of himſelf to his people then, and now; as between a dark ſhadow drawn with a cole in compariſon of an image. But mark, it was but a ſhadow of the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage; that which we have now is but an image. As there is not ſo much in a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow as in the image, ſo there is not ſo much in the image as in the thing it ſelf. The preſence of God and all his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to his people, and his glory to his people now, it is but an image to that which ſhall be; there ſhall be another preſence of God, another communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and revelation of God hereafter, in another kind then there is now; all that we have now is but an image of that which ſhall be; all that was in the law was but a ſhadow of that image: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſhould have a great deal of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the ſaints.</p>
            <p>Much might be ſaid further, for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting in them now, becauſe they are thoſe that we ſhall live for ever with in heaven. Look to the ſaints eſpecially to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, they are thoſe that we ſhall live
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:121280:90"/> eternally together with in heaven, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are thoſe that we ſhould deligh in. They are thoſe that we ſhall be joyned with for ever in everlaſting halelujahs, before him that ſits upon the throne, and the Lamb. Look upon any ſaint, though he be never ſo mean in gifts and abilities, thou and he ſhall alway joy in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God in glory.</p>
            <p>Yea to be among Gods people is hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it ſelf; they are not onely thoſe that we ſhall be with in heaven, but it is hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>I create a new heaven and a new earth.</hi> Iſa. 65.17. The ſtate of the Church is called heaven, For what is there in heaven but is here? I might ſhew the reſemblance of heaven, and that which that is in heaven is here among us, and therefore if heaven be a place to be delighted in, the ſaints are.</p>
            <p>Therefore have a high eſteem of the ſaints, cloſe with them, and come into as near communion as is poſſible. If they be ſo excellent, and to be delighted in then eſpecially when they are joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether labour all to come in, and joyn
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:121280:90"/> with the ſaints in the neareſt union that is poſſible, in that fellowſhip wherein you may (as near as can be) have fellowſhip onely with them, eſpecially that have the appearance of ſuch.</p>
            <p>The mixture of our communion doth much hinder our delight. Caſt dirt into the fire, and it will damp it: ſo the mixture of ungodly ones, their ſpots and blemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes hinder the delight of Gods people one in another. But now to come among thoſe that your hearts may cloſe with, that you have comfortable evidence, that they are not meer talkers of religion and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours at large, but that the image of God is on them, O what cloſing is there with their hearts, and what admirable good might we enjoy in the communion and ſociety of them. Therefore know that it is one of the greateſt bleſſings that you are capable of in this world to have the neareſt communion with the ſaints next to your immediate communion with God himſelf, it is that which you ſhould ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſteem; and your hearts ſhould work after. Mark that text Pſalme 36. what
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:121280:91"/> is ſaid dour joyning with the people of God, how excellent is thy loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wherein appears the excellency? They ſhall be ſatisfied with the fatneſſe of thy houſe. It is a fruit of the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the loving kindneſſe of God for people to be of Gods houſe, and to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the fatneſſe of it. To have abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Gods creatures, and to have an eſtate, and friends, it is a fruit of Gods kindneſſe, but to joyn with Gods people in a way of worſhip and in the neareſt union it is a fruit of the excellent loving kindneſſe of God to admiration. How excellent is thy loving kindneſſe? it was ſo excellent that he was not able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the excellency of it.</p>
            <p>It is made in Scripture to be the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per inheritance even of the elect of God; to enjoy communion with the people of God, in the type, it is a fruit of the very inheritance of the elect of God; ſo as it is oppoſed to all the vanities of the world. Mark what God ſaith by Iſaiah, <hi>Vanity ſhall take them away, but he that putteth his truſt in me ſhall poſſeſſe the
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:121280:91"/> land, and ſhall inherit my holy mountain.</hi> Now the mountain of God was but a type of Gods Church under the Goſpel, and what God intended to do to the Church. Now ſaith he, vanity ſhall take them away, they ſeek vain things, and they muſt have eſtates, and houſes and trading, and they will ſuffer nothing for the enjoying of ſuch priviledges: but for thoſe that be my own people, they ſhall be in my holy mountain. So in divers places the holy mountain of God is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the inheritance of the ſaints; as the proper enjoying of it is the benefit of them; thoſe that enjoy it are the right heirs of God.</p>
            <p>That was a ſpeciall part of wiſedome of the wiſe merchant, when he had found the pearl, to go and buy the field, he was not content with the pearl, but he buys the field: now the field is the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſaints, the Church of God: the ſaints joyned content themſelves meerly with the knowing of Chriſt, and hope you have part in Chriſt, but buy the field, and labour to enjoy Chriſt with his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:121280:92"/> Think it not enough to go up and down, and now and then get a good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and ſnatch in one place, and in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: but you diſhonour God, and are unthankfull to the grace of God, if you do not what you can to joyn with the ſaints of God in the neareſt communion you can: ſo that you may not onely come to be partakers of the gifts of men; but to look on men as the officers of God ſet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver by Chriſt to watch over your ſouls. This was the intent of Chriſt when he aſcended, he gave gifts, <hi>ſome Prophets, ſome Apoſtles, ſome teachers.</hi> The gifts of Chriſt in his Church to ſhew his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnificence to appoint ordinances to build up the body that there might be relation between people and paſtor. So you are bound to look, not onely to hear now and then, but to joyn with the ſaints in a way of ordinances in the ſtricteſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, that the worſhip of God may be ſet in a ſolemn way according to all his ordinances; that you may look on men as paſtours ſet over you by Chriſt to watch over your ſouls; and herein
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:121280:92"/> the body of Chriſt muſt be built up.</p>
            <p>The exerciſe of gifts this way or that way, though they be uſefull to do good, it is not the ſpeciall ordinance; the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit that chiefly you have is to receive good by men deputed as officers, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by Chriſt though they be men of meaner gifts, then you may expect to be built up. Therefore let it be your care to come to the people of God in the neareſt relation that may be. It is an expreſſion of Calvin concerning that text <hi>ſeek my face,</hi> Pſalm. 27. he interprets ſeeking of Gods face to ſeek God among his people in his ordinances, there is Gods face, ſaith he, though there were no way for me to get my living but by ſcratching in the ground with my nayles, I would ſeek to get my living that way, rather then not be where the face of God is; I would be among the people of God in the way of worſhip, in the way of his ordinances.</p>
            <p>Therefore plead not, it is difficult, and hard. You muſt be willing to ſuffer for this: the people of God formerly were willing to ſuffer. It is obſervable concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:121280:93"/> thoſe godly people among the Jews, when the ten Tribes were divided from the reſt: there were many of the godly whoſe hearts the Lord ſtirred, and they would not be content to be at Samaria, or where J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reboams falſe worſhip of the Calves was ſet up but they would needs go to Jeruſalem, they would obey there, though they ſuffered much before they came thither. You ſhall find an expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Hoſea, that ſhews, that there was watching of thoſe that did go to Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem to intrap them, and catch them, and inflict puniſhments upon them. <hi>Hear ye this O Priests and hearken ye houſe of Iſrael; and give ye eare, O houſe of the King; for judgement is toward you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye have been a ſnare in Mizpah, and a net ſpread upon Tabor.</hi> Hoſ. 5.1. Mizpah and Tabor were two places, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the places of Idolatry and Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, that as they went from Samaria, they were fain to go that way, now they were a ſnare on Mizpah, that is, they watched who did go from Samaria to worſhip at Jeruſalem; yet many went as
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:121280:93"/> the ſtory ſaith, though it were as much as their lives was worth, yet they would go the way to Zion through the valley of tears; and they were contented though they ſuffered much to go through the valley of Bacah that they might come at length to Zion.</p>
            <p>There were many difficulties in the way, and many objections againſt them: but certainly thoſe whoſe hearts the Lord hath touched, they will not be quiet, if there be any nearer union to be enjoyed in the world with the ſaints they will never reſt till they come to it. And God will make the way plain to thoſe that have upright hearts, he will take the ſtumbling blocks out of their way and ſhew them the way that meets God in uprightneſſe. And though there be many ſtumbling blocks, yet God will be at the ſame time in the way, and will take the ſtumbling blocks out of the way. Pſalm. 84. <hi>Bleſſed is he</hi> (ſaith the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt) <hi>in whoſe heart are thy wayes.</hi> If there be any man or woman, though they have not gotten to Gods people in the
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:121280:94"/> neareſt communion, yet if the way to Zion be in their hearts, bleſſed are they. And there is a promiſe too of ſtrength for them; though you find difficulties, God will grant his ſtrength, as Moſes ſaith, <hi>that God in his ſtrength would lead them to his holy habitation.</hi> Exod. 15.13. Indeed it requires the ſtrength of God to lead men to his holy habitation, there are ſo many troubles that lie in their way.</p>
            <p>There is a prophecy that men ſhould bring to Zion men and women, in Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots, and Litters. Now Litters are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments to convey weak ones in; ſo that there is no excuſe for thoſe that are old and weak; what ſhall we do? Where God ſtirs the heart, though they be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in Litters, though they be never ſo weak if it be poſſible, they will go tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. That which we delight in we are never quiet till we enjoy it; and every one of Gods people can ſay, thoſe that are excellent in earth are all my delight. I find ſweetneſſe, when I find but one or two of them; O if there were more of
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:121280:94"/> them, what delight ſhould I have!</p>
            <p>To conclude, if there be ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the ſaints, in this world, what will there be in the ſaints in heaven! If it be worth the greateſt labour and pains to joyn with them here, what will it be worth to have everlaſting communion with them! For then we ſhall not onely have communion with a few, but with all the Patriarchs, Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Martyrs, and all the worthies of God. If there be delight in one; what will there be when there ſhall be all, and we ſhall delight in all, when they ſhall be ſpotleſſe! Now it damps our joy the weakneſſe that we ſee in the ſaints that are ſincere; we ſee many froward paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in them, many paſſionate fits that makes their communion uncomfortable many times: but then there ſhall be no more ſullenneſſe, or paſſion, there ſhall be no more indiſcretion or weokneſſe as there is now. Now to come to joyn with any, if there be a little grace to ſanctifie them, there is abundance of weakneſſe: but then we ſhall come to have commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:121280:95"/> with ſaints that ſhall be all filled with God; there ſhall be nothing but God in them. Men now have excellent gifts, but their corruptions ſo darken the communion, that it is not delightfull. But then all ſhall be in holineſſe, there ſhall be nothing but God in them.</p>
            <p>And they ſhall be alway exerciſed in praiſing God: it is comfortable to be with the ſaints in civill affairs, in eating and drinking, but it is more delightfull to pray, and to have the Sacrament, and to conferre graciouſly with them: But then hereafter we ſhall be in heaven with them, and ſhall never do any thing but alway worſhip, and praiſe God night and day together. One day with Gods people what is it worth? when it is gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly ſpent in holy exerciſes, how de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull is it, if it were not for the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſſe of the fleſh: but then we ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver depart, nor never be weary. Now when we come to Gods people, to be with them an hour, or a day or two, it is delightfull, but this doth not laſt long: but we ſhall be ſo with them then as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:121280:95"/> to part how delightfull will that be?</p>
            <p>And all this in our fathers houſe, in the preſence of God, where there ſhall be no enemy to hurt us, and before our fathers children and friends delight in one another in a ſtrange place: but in their fathers houſe, in the preſence of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they have more delight, we ſhall then all come before God our father.</p>
            <p>To be the children of God in a dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, as the Saints and Martyrs, they found it delightfull: but then we ſhall be ever in the pallace of our Father, before the King even in his Majeſty and glory. It were worth our labour to get heaven, if it were but for this, to be with Paul that gracious ſpirit: if it were but to be with one or two of the worthies of God; but then we ſhall come to heaven to all the Saints, Saith Sizillanum, ſpeaking of death, O famous day, I ſhall be delivered from this world, to Cato, and to ſuch wiſe men, my ſoul ſhall go to them, and ſhall converſe no more with theſe people in the world, a heathen had ſo much in his morall virtues. But now the children
<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:121280:96"/> of God how comfortable may they die, how famous a day will it be to them? Here through Gods mercy I had much ſweetneſſe in the ſaints of God, I deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in them in the world, now I go to change my place but not my company, it was the dying ſpeech of Doctor Preſton, I go where I ſhall converſe with thoſe that I lived with here. He meant eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, God and Chriſt. We change our place and our individuall company for a while, but we go to a place where we ſhall meet with them again. As it is a commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church, we are come to an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable number of the ſouls of ſaints made perfect, &amp;c. It ſhall be fullfilled in heaven, we are to go to an innumerable company of angels, &amp; to all the ſouls of the excellent on earth, that are made perfect.</p>
            <p>Therefore, as ever you would have communion with them hereafter, delight your ſelves in their communion here, the more comfortable delight you have in them here, the more comfortable aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance you ſhall have of communion with them hereafter.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
